怎么了 你还好吗?
Yeah, you okay?
我们成功了
We have it.
安德烈亚斯 我们成功了
Andreas, we have it.
实验奏效了
It works.
乔根
Jorgen.
我很荣幸
It gives me great pleasure
有请
to welcome
研究所所长同时也是我的老朋友
the director of the institute and my old friend,
安德烈亚斯·雅克布森博士
Dr. Andreas Jacobsen.
谢谢大家 谢谢佩雷拉博士
Thank you. Thank you, Dr. Pereira.
75年前 内莉·埃德瓦森夫人
Seventy-five years ago, Mrs. Nellie Edvardsen,
为了减轻一战期间
overcome with guilt by the fortune
她亡夫的家族通过制造芥子气
her late husband's family had amassed
来敛财的罪恶感
producing mustard gas during World War I,
成立了这家研究所
founded our institute
这样科学的奇迹
so that the wonders of science
就可以用来帮助人类
could instead be used to help mankind.
在20世纪50年代
In the 1950s,
研究所将人口过剩确定为
the institute identified over-population
人类最大的长期威胁
as mankind's single greatest long-term threat,
它是导致现如今所有灾难的原因--
the cause of all the catastrophes we are seeing today--
极端天气气候事件
extreme climate and weather events,
以及对食品安全和水安全的破坏性影响
and the devastating impact on food and water security.
在我们多年前设想的多种解决方案中
Among the many solutions we conceived so many years ago,
有一个...
one...
当时看起来非常艰巨
which seemed then so ambitious, so
超出我们能力范围的方案
out of our grasp
终于成功了
has finally borne fruit.
今天 我们很自豪地宣布
And today we are proud to unveil
我们坚信能够解决人类最大问题的
what we fervently believe to be the only practical,
唯一既实际又人道且具包容性的补救办法
humane and inclusive remedy to humanity's greatest problem.
我的同事
My colleague,
乔根·阿斯比恩森博士将会对他的发现做一个介绍
Dr. Jorgen Asbjornsen will now present his findings.
准备好了吗 博士?
Are you ready, doctor?
准备好了
Yes, I'm ready.
请坐
Please take your seats.
女士们 先生们 请坐
Please sit down, ladies and gentlemen, please.
Please take your seats, ladies and gentlemen.
非常感谢
Thank you very much. Thank you.
谢谢 谢谢大家
Thank you, thank you.
佩雷拉博士 各位尊敬的同事
Dr. Pereira, esteemed colleagues.
五年前
Five years ago,
在前辈研究的基础上
building on the research of our predecessors at the institute,
我的团队和我发现了一种反应过程
my team and I discovered a process
通过这个过程 所有有机物质
by which all organic material can be reduced
可以在细胞级别减少约
at the cellular level by a ratio of approximately
2744比1的比例
2,744 to one.
一个1米8的大男人通过这个反应过程
Such a process converts a man of 1.8 meters
可以缩小到12.9厘米
to just 12.9 centimeters.
大量的动植物
A wide array of flora and fauna
被运用到这个实验中
were subjected in this process
除了一些鱼类和贝类
and with the exception of some fish and shellfish,
完全没有发现任何负面作用
absolutely no side effects were detected.
灯光
Please, lights.
过程的安全性得到确保之后
Once the safety of the procedure was confirmed,
36位勇敢的志愿者
thirty-six brave volunteers
加上我和我的妻子安妮·海伦
joined my wife Anne-Helene and me
成为首批进行细胞缩小术的人类
as the very first humans to undergo cellular reduction.
整个过程很快且无痛苦
The process is short and painless,
略有些轻微的
with only the mild discomfort of removal
牙齿和肢体更换的不适感
and replacement of dental and other prosthetics.
受试者处于轻度睡眠状态
The subjects are placed under light sedation,
通过短暂的休息
and after a brief rest,
在1到2个小时内可完全恢复
fully recover within an hour or two.
一旦完成 我们的小村庄
Once completed, our little village,
只有77平方米
just seven meters by eleven meters,
被放置在透气的保护壳中
was place inside a gas-permeable enclosure
以免我们受到天气
designed to protect us from the hazards of weather,
动物和昆虫的伤害
animals and insects.
就这样 我们开始共同生活在
Thus we set about to live together
世界上第一个自给自足
in the world's very first self-sustaining
的小型社区里
community of the small.
在我的手中
I hold here in my hand
是过去4年36个人产生的
all of the uncompostable waste
所有不可分解的垃圾
produced by 36 people over four years.
在今天下午的会议上
In this afternoon's session,
我们将会针对在两三百年内使世界由大变小这个议题
we will outline our proposal for a two to three-hundred year transition
概述我们的方案
for the world to transform from big into small.
但现在
But for now,
我想介绍一群非常特殊的人
I'd like you all to meet some very special people.
干得好!
Bravo!
太棒了!
Yes!
好样的!
Bravo!
请看 这位是小罗尼 Nesthritt
And look, there is little Ronnie Nesthritt,
出生的第一个微型宝宝
the first small baby ever born.
以及他的小妹妹乌莉卡
And his new little sister Ulrikke.
...爱德华森研究所
of the Edvardsen Institute,
现在只有10厘米高 重约18克
himself now only ten centimeters tall and weighing just 18 grams,
显示了这项发现的可行性
explained the rationale behind the invention.
天呐!太疯狂了 简直太疯狂了!
Wow! That is wild, isn't it? Just wild.
什么事 霍莉
Say, Holly,
你继续去接外卖单 谢谢
you can go ahead and put the take-out order in, thanks.
-是你吗? -是的
-Is that you? -Yeah.
饿了吗?
You hungry?
我一个小时前吃过了
I ate about an hour ago.
我不知道你要来
I didn't know when you were coming.
你知道我要带些吃的来
You knew I was bringing food.
我还特地给你打了电话
I called you and asked you specifically.
-我刚吃了芝麻鸡 -然而你还是吃过了
-I just had sesame chicken. -And then you go and eat.
我还是很饿
I'm still hungry.
"尖叫预谋"
screams premeditation.
"人们尚不了解他的新书"
Yet relatively few people knew about his new book.
你今天看新闻了吗?
Did you see the news today?
那个瑞典微型人
About the little Swedish man?
挪威人
Norwegian.
看了 海伦打电话过来让我看的
Yeah, Helen called to tell me to turn on the TV.
有什么他们不敢想的呢
What won't they think of next.
难以置信 自登月之后最大的一件事 并且更大
Unbelievable. Biggest thing since landing on the moon. Bigger.
唔
Mm.
我不懂
I don't get it.
为什么会有人愿意对自己这样做呢
Why would anybody want to do that to himself?
他们能把人类缩小
They can shrink people down,
飞向火星
fly to mars,
但他们却不能治愈我的纤维肌痛?
and they can't cure my fibromyalgia?
即使明天世界末日了
And all this fuss about the environment
还在对环境问题大题小做
though the world's gonna end tomorrow.
我很痛苦
I'm in pain.
几乎不能呼吸
I can't breathe.
那难道不重要吗?
Doesn't that matter?
很多人都有病痛 妈妈
Lots of people are in pain, Mom.
各种各样的病痛
In all sorts of ways.
你好 卡尔曼
Hola Carmen.
准备好了吗
Are you ready?
用力 用力
Strong, strong.
和往常差不多还是...
Is it usually or more like...
有点刺痛
tingling?
-更像刺痛 -刺痛 明白了
-More like tingling. -Tingling. Okay.
缩小人类技术就像一辆失控的列车
This downsizing thing is simply runaway train technology
对世界经济
that's having a devastating impact
有破坏性的影响
on our world economy.
我们已经损失了数十亿的消费支出
We're losing billions of dollars in consumer spending already.
对建筑业 汽车行业 房地产和国防
It's hurting us in construction,
造成了损失
automobile, housing, and defense.
政治方面尤其如此
And then of course, when we get to politics,
-以色列人缩小巴勒斯坦人 -荣恩...
-Israelis shrinking Palestinians, -Ron...
非洲独裁者
African dictators
-缩小敌对族群 -荣恩 听着 荣恩
-shrinking rival ethnic groups. -Ron. Look, Ron.
社会的变革
In any major transformation of society,
伴随着成长的阵痛吗?
are there serious growing pains?
当然
Sure.
但就目前的数量和体积
But at current mass and volume,
人类生命在地球上是不可延续的
human life on Earth is unsustainable.
他说的有点道理
You know, that one guy makes a good point.
和我同一街道的一户人家为了变小而刚搬走
This family on my block just moved away to get small,
他们的房子就矗立在那儿
now their house is just sittin' there.
他们的行为让所有人的价值观受到了冲击
Makin' everybody's values take a dive is what they're doin'.
就在我试着筹钱的时候
Just when I'm tryin' to refinance.
马勒尼觉得我应该接受这项手术来减肥
Marlene thinks I should do it just to lose the weight.
兄弟 你和我都需要做
You and me both, buddy.
嘿 dee 打包好了吗
Hey, Dee, is that take-out order about ready?
嘿 亲爱的 我带了吃的
Hey, honey, I brought food.
我不饿
I'm not hungry.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
我有点头疼
I have a splitting headache.
店里超级忙
The store was super busy and
卡尔拉是个该死的婊子
Carla was a total bitch on wheels.
我觉得我要吐了
I feel like I'm gonna throw up.
让我帮你按摩按摩脖子
Here, wait, let me do the neck thing.
好啊 按摩一下
Yeah, do the little neck thing.
嗯
Mm.
放轻松 宝贝
Just relax, honey.
把重量都放我手上
Let me take all the weight.
这是一个有着大壁炉
Okay, here's the beautiful formal living room
装修精美的客厅
with the wonderful fireplace.
到这里来 我们有
And come around here, we have
一个有宽阔早餐区的厨房
a nice big breakfast area for the kitchen.
很大的用餐空间
Big eating area.
这个厨房非常棒
And this kitchen is just a complete wow.
不 这房子很棒 只是...
No, it's awesome. Just...
或许我们可以再看看本森那栋
maybe we should look again at that place in Benson.
来吧 让我们看完剩下的
Come on, let's just check out the rest.
这里很棒
This is great in here,
双烤箱 六口燃气灶
double oven, six burner gas stove.
这边还有一个食品储藏室
It's got this wonderful butler's pantry over here.
-噢 嘿 肖恩 -噢 嘿 保罗 你好吗?
-Oh, hey, Sean. -Oh, hey, Paul, how you doin'?
不错
Good.
我看起来胖吗?
Do I look fat?
不 你看着很帅
No, you look very handsome.
麻醉科 嗯?
Anesthesiology, huh?
我妻子说我能不用药物使人入睡 所以
My wife says I put people to sleep even without the drugs, so.
很奇怪你居然醒着
Surprised you're still awake.
他每周要把这个笑话讲两次
He uses that joke like twice a week.
你研究什么领域 保罗?
What's your field, Paul?
呃 职业治疗
Uh, occupational therapy.
不错
Okay.
哦 类似职业咨询
Oh, like-like career counseling?
呃 不是 就是物理疗法
Uh, no, it's just like physical therapy
但专注于工伤和恢复领域
but focused on workplace injuries and rehab,
肢体机械性劳损 下背部等等
repetitive stress, lower back, that sort of thing.
有许多肩部方面的问题
A lot of shoulder problems.
我公司在奥马哈牛排店上面
I-I'm in-house over at Omaha Steaks.
-他有很多文书工作要做 -是的 嗯...
-He does a lot of paperwork. -Yeah, well...
我时不时自己也会得腕管综合症
I get a little carpal tunnel of my own from time to time.
我有同感
Tell me about it.
如今的药品就是用来收拾烂摊子的
Medicine these days is all about covering your ass.
但你不是在林肯医院工作吗?
But weren't you pre-med down in Lincoln?
记性真好 不错 我呆了两年
Good memory, yeah. I put in two years
但我妈妈病得非常严重
uh, then my mom got real sick
所以我搬回奥马哈来照顾她
so I moved back to Omaha to take care of her.
实际上我想成为一名外科医生
I wanted to be a surgeon, actually.
说不定我们会一起工作
You know, we might've ended up working together.
你说不定会是我的麻醉师
I...you could've been my anesthesiologist.
-听起来不错 -对的
-How 'bout that? -Yeah.
哦 天呐!不可能
Oh, my God! No way.
我看到她向这桌走来
? I saw her heading to the table ?
步伐活像一只黑猫
? Like a tall walking big black cat ?
戴夫？
Dave?
是戴夫 戴夫·约翰逊
It's Dave, Dave Johnson.
以及卡罗!
And Carol!
能搭把手吗?
Can I have a hand?
我...我听说他要来
I-I heard he was coming.
真没想到
I had no idea.
我从没想过他会把自己变小
He never struck me as the kind of guy who'd go get small.
哇喔!
Wow!
有个人夺门而出 桌椅乱飞
A-jumping out of doors and tables
不知道是谁开始射击?
When I heard somebody shootin' a gun
然后检察官拷了我的左手?
Well the DA was pumping my left hand
但她牵着我的右手
Ah, but she was a-holding my right
-大家好! -你们好!
-Hey, everybody! -Hi!
-嘿 -你好
-Hey. -Hi.
希望我们没有打扰你们
Hope we're not intruding.
-没有 -没有 戴夫
-No. -No, Dave.
嘿 安迪
Hey, Andy?
你能帮卡罗倒一杯 呃...
Could you get Carol a, uh...
琴汤尼
Uh, gin and tonic.
一杯琴汤尼
A gin and tonic.
加酸橙
With lime.
事实上 我们一开始没打算来
Well, actually, we weren't planning on coming at all at first.
但 你懂的 我们开始收到很多邮件
But then, you know, we started getting all the e-mails.
再加上我妹妹进行了肿瘤切除手术
Plus my sister was having a lump removed.
感谢上帝 她恢复得很好
I mean, she's-she's fine, thank God.
但我还是得来看看她
But I still needed to see her.
旅行怎么样?
So, what's traveling like?
你们是怎么从新墨西哥州过来的?
How'd you guys get up here from New Mexico?
天 非常棒
Oh, gosh, it's great.
现在的航班对微型人越来越友好了
Yeah, the airlines are getting more and more small-friendly.
座位都在头等舱
All the seats are first-class...
在佛罗里达州待了几年后 我们搬到了拉斯维加斯
So after a couple of years in Florida, we moved out to Vegas.
然后...
And that...
我记得那是我们最后一次聊天吧
Yeah, I think that's the last time we talked.
是的 拉斯维加斯
Yeah. Well, Vegas wasn't
不适合我
such a good choice for me, as it turns out.
我在那染上了一些坏习惯
Got into some real bad habits.
差不多跌到人生谷底了
Pretty much hit rock bottom.
我跟你讲 其他的女人肯定会逃得远远的
Tell ya, any other woman would've run for the hills.
但卡罗 她是一个圣人
Carol, man, she's a saint.
她一直陪着我
She stuck with me.
但我需要从头开始
But I really had to come clean about everything.
重新来过
I-I mean everything.
你懂的 差不多这样
You know...almost.
所以 你就决定...
So, the decision to...
是的 就是这样
Well, that's the thing.
我们都需要做出改变
We both needed the change.
按下重置键 从头开始
Hit the reset button. Start all over.
嗯 知道自己做出贡献的感觉
Well, and plus, it must feel good to know
一定很棒
you're really making a difference.
你指那些拯救地球的胡话?
You mean all that crap about saving the planet?
对
Yeah.
缩小身体就是自救
Downsizing is about saving yourself.
它减轻了压力
I-It takes the pressure right off.
特别是资金压力
Especially money pressure.
我不像我其他家人那样雄心勃勃
I'm just not driven and ambitious like the rest of my family.
卡罗和我现在活得像皇室一样
And now, Carol and I, we live like kings.
我还是住在从小长大的房子里
I'm still living in the same house I grew up in.
奥德丽特别希望我们搬家
I mean, Audrey's dying for us to move
但是我们非常拮据
but we're really strapped.
我的意思是 我才还清我的学生贷款
I mean, shit, I just finished paying off my student loans.
这个嘛
Yeah, well...
听着 如果你考虑清楚了
Listen, if you ever start thinkin' about it seriously,
这是我的一点建议 呃...
here's my two cents, uh...
那里有很多小型社区
There's a lot of small communities croppin' up out there, but
但别搞错
don't mess around.
悠闲境才是你真正想去的社区
Leisureland's where you wanna be.
最好的房子 最好的设备 最好的医生
Best houses, best appliances, best doctors.
有精彩绝伦的演唱会巡演
They book all the big concert tours.
有让人垂涎欲滴的餐厅
They got all the great restaurants.
孩子们爱死了芝士蛋糕
The kids love Cheesecake Factory.
而悠闲境里有三家芝士蛋糕工厂
And Leisureland's got three of 'em.
我说这些不是为了向你推销
And hey, I'm not just saying all this for the referral credit.
别误会
Just so you know.
我喜欢小卡罗 她现在过得非常好
I liked little Carol. She's got a lot on the ball.
她在读她一直想读的书
She's reading books she always wanted to read.
她会说意大利语
She's taking Italian.
她过得从没这么健康过
And she's never been fitter.
他们看起来确实非常开心
Well, they sure seem happy.
戴夫说他打鼓打得越来越好了
Dave says he's getting pretty good on the drums.
明年他们将带孩子
Next year, they're taking the kids out of school
在托斯卡纳的姐妹城市里住上六个月
to spend six months at a sister city in Tuscany.
烹饪课 瑜伽 品酒会
Cooking classes, yoga, wine-tasting,
应有尽有
the whole nine yards.
你好 萨弗 奥德丽 我是米洛
Hey, Saf, Audrey, it's Milo.
有个坏消息
Bad news.
你在银行的抵押贷款被拒绝了
Your mortgage application at First National bounced back.
保险商觉得收入与负债比不太合理--
The underwriter didn't like the income to debt ratios--
比例有点过大了
they're a little excessive.
我不确定你能不能想想办法
I-I don't know if you can come up with
降低10%到15%
another ten-fifteen percent down.
如果你可以 修改一下...
If you could, maybe goose it up a little bit...
我们很快就会知道它适不适合我们了
And then we'll be able to tell right away if it's for us or not.
对 别浪费时间了
Yeah, so let's not waste a lot of time.
要是我们到圣达菲到早了 我们还可以做个按摩
Maybe if we get to Santa Fe early, we can get a massage.
听起来不错
Sounds good to me.
相拥着跳舞
Out together dancin' cheek to cheek
天堂
Heaven
我宛如置身天堂
I'm in heaven
这一周所有的关心
And the cares that hung around me
都在我左右?
through the week
就如同不再眷顾赌徒的幸运女神消失了一样
Seem to vanish like a gambler's lucky streak
当我们一起脸贴着脸跳舞时
When we're out together dancin' cheek to cheek
欢迎大家
Welcome, everybody!
我是杰夫·罗诺斯基 高级产品专家
I'm Jeff Lonowsky, Senior Product Specialist
悠闲境的产权拥有者
and happy homeowner here at Leisureland Estates.
你们玩得开心吗?
You havin' a good time?
-是的 -是的
-Yeah. -Yeah.
加把劲 大家 你们可比我大多了
Come on, guys, you're a heck of a lot bigger than I am.
大声点! 你们玩得开心吗?
Make some noise! Are you havin' a good time?
-开心! -开心!
-Yeah! -Yeah!
这还差不多
That's more like it.
你们觉得我这地方怎么样?
So, what do you think of my place?
很漂亮吧?
Pretty nifty, huh?
这是我梦想中的房子
It's the house of my dreams.
哎 我会说这是所有人梦想的房子
Heck, I'd say this is the house of anybody's dreams.
为什么呢? 以前平庸如我的人得工作20年
Why, an average guy like me would have to work twenty,
30年 甚至40年才买得起这样
thirty, maybe forty years to afford a place like this,
的房子
if ever.
来看看里面有什么
And just wait till you see what's inside.
噢
Oh.
杰夫?
Jeff?
你别再未经我允许就请客人来
You've gotta stop inviting guests over without telling me.
噢 对不起 劳拉 我只是在--
Oh, sorry, Laura. I was only--
我刚忙完 准备泡个澡放松一下呢
I mean, I finally just got in the tub to relax after such a busy day.
忙了些什么呢 亲爱的?
Busy doing what, sweetheart?
噢 好多事情
Oh, no end of things.
我先是上了一堂网球课 然后做了个按摩
First I took a tennis lesson and had a massage.
不错
Nice.
然后和姐妹们吃了顿美味的午餐
And then after a gourmet lunch with the girls,
嗯 我们控制不住
well, we couldn't help ourselves
去逛了市中心那家新的罗格特珠宝店
so we popped into that new Loget's jewelry store downtown.
啊哦 罗格特的 花了我多少?
Uh-oh, Loget's. What's than gonna cost me?
安静 杰夫 没花多少
Now, Jeff, you hush. I was really good.
只是一条钻石手镯
Just another diamond bracelet.
只有一条钻石手镯? 听起来可一点都不像你
Just a diamond bracelet? That doesn't sound like you.
猜对了 我不想拆了一整套首饰
You're right, I don't like to break up a set.
所以我还买了配套的钻石耳环
So, I got matching diamond earrings
以及配套的钻石项链
and a matching diamond necklace.
都是互相不冲突的材料 而且用铂金镶嵌
All conflict-free, and set in platinum.
多少钱 劳拉
How much, Laura?
多少钱 劳拉?
哦 但是杰夫 我戴着这么好看 你应该看
Oh, but Jeff, they look so good on me, and you should see--
噢 杰夫 我戴着它们非常漂亮 你应该看看--
多少钱 劳拉？
How much, Laura?
- 唉 杰夫  - 我说多少钱
-Well, Jeff... -I said how much?
八十三美金
Eighty-three dollars.
八十三美金 你疯了吗
Eighty-three dollars? Are you crazy?
那是我们整整两个月的食物预算啊
Why, that's practically our food budget for two whole months!
总体来看的话 如果你们卖掉现在的房子
Putting it all together, if you liquidate your current home,
车 和其他财产
cars and other assets,
买一所至尊级房产
and purchase a Regency-level estate--
记住了那可是等同1100平米的房子
remember that's a 12,000 square foot equivalent home
建在等同6000平米的庄园上 基价在六万三千美元
on a 1.5 acre equivalent lot-- at a base price of $63,000.
之后购买健康和健身套
Then the Health and Fitness package--
那个4500美金 你可得买这个
that's $4,500, you're gonna wanna get that.
包括健身房 泳池 桑拿 蒸汽浴室 热浴缸 和网球场
It's gym, pool, sauna, steam, hot tub, and a tennis court.
还有两个成人的医疗程序费
Then the medical procedures for two adults.
那是一万五千美金
That's $15,000.
但保险一点都不包括这些吗
But does insurance cover any of that?
不 但在至尊级
No, but at the Regency
你可以取得大幅折扣
level you qualify of a substantial discount.
而且别忘了联邦税收抵免
And don't forget the federal tax credit.
- 对 对  - 对吧
-Right, right. -Right?
那 看一下你们目前的债务
So, taking a look at your current debt,
你们的养老金和其余存款
you retirement and your other savings,
你们拥有十五万二千美金资产
you are at $152,000 in equity.
两位 这可是个非常舒服的数
People, that is a very comfortable number.
舒服 这些钱听起来根本不够啊
Comfortable‘? That doesn't sound like nearly enough.
- 嗯  - 不是的
-Yeah. -Well, no.
看 你必须看看这行 奥黛丽
See, you have to look at this column, Audrey.
等同财产
Equivalent value.
你们可完全处于蓝筹区里
You're solidly inside the Blue Chip zone.
在悠闲境里面你们的十五万两千美金等价为一千两百五十万
In Leisureland your $152,000 translates to $12.5 million--
可供生活享受
to live on, for life.
我是说 真的
I mean, come on!
- 哦  - 嗯
-Oh. -Well.
等等 如果这么好的话
Hold on, if this is such a good thing,
为什么你没去变小
how come you haven't done it?
我毫不犹豫就会这么做
I would do it in a heartbeat
但我丈夫做了髋关节手术
but my husband had a hip replacement
所以他不能做
so he's ineligible.
那 你们怎么看
So, what do you think?
至尊级是你们的第一选择吗
Would the Regency level be your first choice?
还是我应该给你们介绍更奢侈一点的选择
Or should should I show you something a little more deluxe?
宝贝 你去看着选吧
Honey, why don't you just go ahead and pick.
我只想让你开心
I just want you to be happy.
这是个好丈夫
That's a good husband.
看看这个
Take a look at this.
嘿 这个热狗机多少钱
Hey, how much for the hotdog cooker?
4美元
Four dollars.
我能出一美元
I'll give you a dollar.
成交
Sold.
继续好好锻炼 别犯懒 看
Keep up with the exercises. Don't get lazy. Look.
我给你整理好了
I laminated it for you,
这样你真的没有理由不做了
so you literally have no excuse not to do it.
好 谢谢 保罗 太谢谢了
Okay, thanks, Paul. Thanks a lot.
没事
You bet.
或许有一天我和我妻子也会变小
Maybe someday me and my wife will get small
然后我们就去看你们
and we'll come down and see ya.
嗯 那就太好了 但同时...
Well, I'd love that. But in the meantime...
- 好吗  - 好的
-Okay? -All right.
- 每晚锻炼15分钟就好  - 好的
-Just 15 minutes every night. -Okay.
- 会改变你的生活的  - 谢了 保罗
-It'll change your life. -Thanks, Paul.
再见 戴夫
See ya, Dave.
我们在这里 因为保罗·萨弗拉尼克
We're here to wish Paul Safranek
一路顺风 保罗 我们会想你 享受品味天地生活
即将搬去悠闲境 与他道别
farewell as he moves on to Leisureland.
而且我们只求他最好 别无所求
And we wish him nothing but the best.
祝你和奥德蕾好运
Good luck to you and Audrey.
谢了 鲍勃
Thanks, Bob.
你们就没考虑过宝藏岛他家吗
And you guys didn't consider Treasure Island
就在棕榈沙漠那边
out in Palm Desert?
嗯 我们去看过了 但
Well, we checked it out, but
我是说 我觉得不错
I mean, I liked it all right.
但奥德蕾觉得他们的设施有点差
But Audrey thought they were a little stingy with the amenities.
我是说 尤其是看在他们每月
I mean, especially given what they're charging
收那么多维护费的份上
in monthly maintenance.
而我就转向保罗说"好 你赢了"
And I just turned to Paul and said, "Okay, you win."
我们做吧
Let's go for it.
我们会很想你的
We're just gonna miss you so much.
哦 Gina 我也会想你的
Oh, Gina, I'm gonna miss you too.
听着 又不是我们就要死了 好吗
Well, look, it's not like we're dying, okay?
我们只是要搬家
We're just relocating.
我们会每年至少回来一次的 或许更频繁呢
And we'll be back at least once a year. Maybe more.
- 嗨 爸  - 甜心
-Hi, Dad. -Sweetheart.
嗯 很抱歉你母亲不能过来
Yeah, well, sorry your mom couldn't bring herself to come.
但她转达她的爱
But she sends her love
而且我们明天下午在家里等你
and we're expecting you at the house tomorrow afternoon.
- 很高兴你能过来 拉里  - 嘿 保罗
-Glad you could make it, Larry. -Hey, Paul.
你喝点什么 爸
What can I get you, Dad?
嘿 我去吧 - 你们就待在这 好吗
Look, why don't I-- here, you guys visit. Um...?
- 啤酒  - 好的
-Beer. -Yeah.
- 随便什么啤酒  - 好的 马上就来
-Just any beer. -That's great, okay, comin' up.
我希望妈别这么不能接受
I wish Mom weren't taking it so hard.
嗯 你了解你妈
Well, you know your mother.
老实说 我一开始也有点怀疑
Frankly, I was a little skeptical about it myself at first.
但 你记得杰瑞 Gross吗
Say, you remember Jerry Gross?
嗯 我那天给他打了个电话
Well, I called him the other day.
他和Bev退休之后
He and Bev retired down there.
做了你们这些孩子做的这个缩小
Did the whole shrinking thing that you kids are doing.
他说他们过的很好 再好不过了
He says they're getting along just fine, never better.
他说他每天都觉得更年轻
He says he feels younger every day
还有一美元能买到一千美元的东西
and that a dollar buys a thousand dollars worth of stuff.
当然因为Bev要用的那些药他们需要这个
Of course they need that with all the medication Bev takes.
但 ... 嗯
But, uh... yeah.
你知道的 我能看到优点
You know, I... I see the appeal.
尤其是那里零犯罪 我一直和你妈说
Apparently there's zero crime, I keep telling your mother.
特别安全
It's very safe.
嗯 我们还是会担心
Yeah, we worry.
我还年轻的时候 那时候我丢了...
When I was younger and, and uh, and then I-I lost the...
嘿
Hey...
你们是那群要变小的人 是吧
You guys are the ones getting small, right?
呃 对 我和我妻子
Uh, that's right, my wife and I.
真不错
Good for you.
无意冒犯 但是...
No offense, but um...
你觉得你们那么小
do you think if you're that small
你们还和我们剩下的正常大小的人
you should still have all the same rights as the rest of us
有相同的权利吗
normal-sized people?
我是说 就像投票权
I mean, like the right to vote?
为什么不呢
Why wouldn't we?
哦 天 说起来 嗯
Oh, well, jeez, let's see, um...
你们不会买那么多产品
You don't buy as many products,
你们不会缴那么多税务
you're not paying as much sales tax,
你们有些人甚至连收入税都不缴
some of you aren't even paying any income tax.
我是说 你们没有真的在
I mean, you're not really
参与我们的经济 不是吗
participating in our economy, are you?
- 嘿  - 我是说 实际上你们在消耗我们的
-Hey. -I mean, in fact you're costin' us
- 嘿 嘿  - 钱和工作
-Hey. Hey! -money and jobs.
够了
That's enough.
我们在这聊的开心呢
We're just having a good time here.
嘿 我只是问了一个简单的学术问题 好吗
Hey, I'm just askin' a simple academic question, all right?
- 你知道吗 我觉得你们  - 嘿 蒂姆 蒂姆...
-You know what, I think you guys -Hey, Tim, Tim...
最多一人有四分之一票
should have a quarter of a vote at most.
- 我是说 那就算大方了  - 蒂姆
-I mean, that's pretty generous. -Tim.
坐下 蒂姆
Take a seat, Tim.
- 喔 喔 喔  - 滚远点成吗
-Whoa, whoa, whoa! -Why don't you take a walk.
冷静点 大家伙
Cool your jets, big guy!
你知道吗 或许八分之一票
You know what, maybe an eighth of a vote, if that.
而且你也需要变小点 老兄
And you could use a little small, buddy.
嗯 坐下吧
Yeah, sit down.
嘿
Hey!
我这个正常大小的人能来杯正常大小的啤酒吗
Can I get a normal-sized beer for a normal-sized guy?
我一直觉得我忘了什么
I keep thinking I forgot something.
要搬进来了 是吧
Moving to town, are you?
什么
How's that?
我说你们要搬到悠闲境了
I said you're moving to Leisureland.
你们看着是很不错的一对儿
You look like a nice young couple.
谢谢
Thanks.
你们从哪来
Where you from?
呃 奥马哈
Uh, Omaha.
我来自斯波坎
Spokane.
紧张吗
Nervous?
嗯 你懂的 有一点
Yeah, you know, uh, a little.
没必要
Don't be.
这会是你们做过的最好的事
It's the best thing you'll ever do.
在你们的许可下
With your permission,
我将记录你们对下列问题的回答
I'm going to record your answers to the following questions.
我可以开始录像吗
May I begin the recording?
- 当然  - 好
-Sure. -Yeah.
请说出你们法律意义上的全名
Please state your full legal names.
奥德蕾·勒斯蒂格·萨弗拉尼克
Audrey Lustig Safranek.
保罗·诺瑞斯·萨弗拉尼克
Paul Norris Safranek.
而你 奥德蕾·勒斯蒂格·萨弗拉尼克
And do you, Audrey Lustig Safranek,
和你 保罗·诺瑞斯·萨弗拉尼克
and you, Paul Norris Safranek,
是否确认 由你们的个人意志决定
understand that, of your own free will,
你们将被执行永久而不可逆的
you will undergo the permanent and irreversible
医学过程 其常用名为
medical procedure commonly knows as
"缩身"
"Downsizing?"
而在此过程后
And that following the procedure,
你们的身体的质量和体积
your bodies will be approximately
将会缩减到现有的0.0364%
.0364% of their current mass and volume?
对
Yeah.
不好意思 保罗 我需要记录是或否
I'm-I'm sorry Paul, I need a yes or no.
是
Yes.
很好 谢谢你们
Great, thank you.
而你们是否完全同意门关医疗服务
And do you give full consent to Gateway Medical Services
来主理
to administer
常用名为"缩身"的医学过程
the medical procedure commonly known as “downsizing?”
是
Yes.
你们是否了解存在
And do you understand that there exists
大约225000分之一的概率
an approximately one in 225,000 chance
过程可能导致
that the procedure could result
受伤 永久残疾或死亡
in injury, permanent disability or death?
- 是  - 是
-Yes. -Yes.
是
Yes.
萨弗拉尼克？保罗·撒弗拉尼克？
Safranek? Paul Safranek?
有
Yes.
实际上读萨弗拉尼克
It's actually Safranek.
萨弗拉尼克 和我来 先生
Safranek. Come with me, sir.
我们是一起的
We're together.
哦
Oh.
马上会有人引领你去女子机构
Someone will escort you to the women's facility shortly.
你们会分开大概五小时
You will be separated of approximately five hours.
在过程之后 你们会在恢复室里重见
Following the procedure, you'll be reunited in the recovery room.
好的
Okay.
- 那就这样了  - 嗯
-So this is it, then. -Yeah.
- 我们今晚见  - 好
-I'll see you tonight. -Yeah.
我们在另一边见
I'll see you on the other side.
我爱你
I love you.
我也爱你
And I love you, too.
好了 请你上去吧
Okay, let's get you up here.
完毕
All clear!
喔 这次可有几个胖家伙
Oi, we got some real fat one this time.
嘿 今天大家都怎么样
Hey, how's everybody doin' today?
嘿 乔伊斯小姐 我们不错 你呢
Hey, Miss Joyce, doin' good. How you doin'?
我 我很棒 为周末做准备呢
Me, I'm great. Just getting ready for the weekend.
看起来你决定加入我们了
I see you've decided to join us.
这是
Is this...?
结束了吗
Is it over?
欢迎来到悠闲境
Welcome to Leisureland.
你能告诉我你的名字吗
Can you tell me your name?
- 我是保罗·萨弗拉尼克  - 好 很棒
-It's Paul Safranek. -Okay, good.
我猜你肯定饿了
I bet you're hungry.
哦 天啊
Oh, my God.
多可爱啊
Isn't that cute?
大家都爱死了
People just love that.
我马上给你拿点真食物过来
I'll bring you a little snack in a moment.
谢谢 呃
Thanks. Um,
我认为我妻子应该和我一起到这里了
I think my wife was supposed to be here with me.
她叫什么名字
What's her name?
奥德蕾·萨弗拉尼克
让我看看
Let me see.
我们确实今天的安排上有一位奥德蕾·萨弗拉尼克
We do have an Audrey Safranek scheduled for today
但看记录她还没有转到这里
but I don't show her transferred over yet.
她可能还在牙科那边吧 我会去看看的
She's probably just held up in dental. I'll go check.
谢谢你
Thank you.
萨弗拉尼克先生 有你的电话
Mr. Safranek, you've got a call.
哦 谢谢
Oh, thank you.
喂
Hello?
保罗?
哦 奥德蕾 谢天谢地 你在哪呢 宝贝
Oh, Audrey, thank God. Where are you, honey?
别生我的气 求求你别生气
Don't be mad at me. Please don't be mad.
对我已经很艰难了
It's hard enough as it is.
什么很难 等等 你在说什么
What's hard? Wait, what are you talkin' about?
哦 保罗
Oh, Paul!
他们剃光了我的头
They shaved my head.
然后开始剃我的眉毛 我就想
And then they started shaving my eyebrows and I just thought,
"我这是在干什么"
"What am I doing?"
我不能离开我的家庭 我不能离开我的朋友
I can't leave my family. I can't leave my friends.
- 我很抱歉 保罗 我就是不能  - 你在哪
-And I'm sorry, Paul, I just can't. -Where are you?
你在机场吗
Are you at the airport?
别恨我
Don't hate me.
求你不要恨我
Please don't hate me.
好 好 放轻松 就
Okay, okay. Take it easy. Just
打辆出租车回来
get in a taxi and come back
然后我们再谈这事 好吗
and we'll talk about this, okay?
我们回奥马哈去之后我们再一起考虑这事
We'll go back to Omaha and we'll think this through together.
等等
Wait.
你不是要把我丢在这吧
You're not leaving me here.
你不能理解我的感受吗
Can't you understand how I feel?
我感觉很糟
I feel terrible.
我让你失望了 我觉得糟透了
I let you down, I feel awful.
但之后
But then-
之后我意识到我之所以这么做
then I realized I was just doing this
只是因为我想让你开心
because I w-I was trying to make you happy and
我应该多替我自己想想
I should've been thinking more about myself.
替你自己想想
Thinking about yourself?
Thinking about yourself?!
你还没问过我怎么样了
You know, you haven't even asked me how I am!
别吼
Don't yell.
别吼我 不然我就挂了
Don't yell at me or I'll hang up.
你知道我今天经历了什么吗
Do you have any idea what I have been through today?
奥德丽 如果你现在不回来...
Audrey, if you don't come back here right now...
回来看你那么小吗
And see you all small?
我已经够沮丧的了
I'm upset enough already.
你沮丧
You're upset?
我他妈才是那个12厘米高的人
I'm the one who's five fucking inches tall!
嗯 我们很遗憾听到
Well, we're sure sorry to hear
萨弗拉尼克夫人今天无法成行
Mrs. Safranek couldn't make it today.
萨弗拉尼克.
嗯 先在这边打理好一切
Well, it's not a half-bad idea to scout things out
等她来也不完全是坏主意
get everything ready for her.
外膜会阻挡很多紫外线
The net blocks a lot of UV rays,
但还是得把帽子戴上
but you still might wanna put your hat on.
任何时候你想去什么地方
And anytime you wanna go somewhere,
你就随便上一辆这车
you just hop in one of these bad boys.
如果找不到的话
And if they're in short supply, well,
你总可以拼车的
you can always share.
拼车很有意思 我知道的 我这样遇到和一些超级有趣的人
It's fun to share. I know, I've met some super people that way.
超级有趣
Just super.
嗯 多壮观啊
Yeah, isn't that somethin'?
你右手边那里
Over to your right there,
那个大的白色椭圆形建筑是我们的七座体育中心之一
that big, white oval building is one of our seven Sports Centers.
那座配备了
That's the one that houses
世界上最大的室内滑雪设施
the largest indoor skiing facility in the world--
你懂的 相对而言
you know, relatively speaking.
这边是切斯特湖
And over there is Lake Chester...
看上去熟悉吗
Look familiar?
巴林顿房
The Barrington.
我姐姐买了一个 她爱死了
My sister's got one. She loves it.
先生 这是你王国的钥匙
Well, sir, here is the uh, key to your kingdom.
欢迎来到美好生活
Welcome to the good life.
哦 他们在厨房放了常规物品
Oh, they uh, stocked the kitchen with standard items...
但我该警告你小心一件东西那就是乳制品
but one thing I should warn you about is the dairy--
要花一段时间你的胃才能
it takes a while for your stomach
适应牛奶和乳酪
to adjust to the milk and the cheese,
所以少吃点 说是和细菌有关
so go easy on it. Somethin' about the bacteria.
然后小心点热水
And be careful about the hot water.
是一个中心系统接入的 他们把水温提的过高了
It's on one central system and they got that cranked really high.
很惊讶他们还没吃到官司
Surprised they haven't had a lawsuit yet.
哦 这话可不是我说的
Oh, but you didn't hear that from me.
谢了 马特
Thanks Matt.
你是个好人
You're a nice guy.
还有 保罗
And Paul?
感谢你为地球做贡献
Thanks for helping the planet.
该死的
Fuck!
萨弗拉尼克?
是我
That's me.
对了
Okay!
下边是关于的美国新闻
And now from the United States,
很多年以来 国土安全部
where for many years, both the Department of Homeland Security
与移民和归化局
and the Immigration and Naturalization Service
都对这一事宜发出过警告
have been warning about the ease with which
缩小人
downsized people--
从非法移民到潜在恐怖分子
from illegal immigrants to potential terrorists--
都可能渗透过美国边境
could penetrate U.S. Borders.
上周在俄勒冈州尤金的发现
Last week's discovery in Eugene, Oregon
为证明这一说法提供了新的证据
provided new evidence to support that claim.
布莱恩· 法克勒在现场为您报道
Brian Fakler brings us up to date.
这家塔吉特是
This Target is just one of
全国上千所箱装商店之一
thousands of big-box stores around the country
每周要进口接近一百万吨的货物
that import almost a million tons of goods weekly,
多数来自亚洲
most of it from Asia.
上周 尤金的工人打开了这个可疑的电视包装箱
Last week, workers here in Eugene opened a suspicious TV box
发现了17个来自越南的缩小偷渡客
and discovered 17 downsized stowaways from Vietnam,
其中14人已经死亡
14 of them already dead,
另外两个在几小时后于当地医院死亡
two more dying hours later at a local hospital.
在周五 唯一生还者 一个名为陈玉兰的女性
On Friday, the lone survivor, a woman named Ngoc Lan Tran,
转移至一家
was transferred to a
位于新墨西哥州悠闲境地产的医院
hospital at Leisureland Estates in New Mexico,
其被普遍认为是国家顶尖的缩小人医院
widely considered the country's top medical center for the small.
医生们不得已截去一部分受感染的腿
Doctors were forced to amputate a portion of an infected leg,
今天据描述她的状况以趋于稳定
and today her condition is described as fair but stable.
根据来自
According to a statement
国土安全部的供述
from the Department of Homeland Security,
陈小姐宣称她因
Ms. Tran claims to have been jailed
政治与环境方面的运动被囚禁
for her political and environmental activism,
在一所越南监狱中
and was miniaturized against her will
随后被迫缩小
in a Vietnamese prison facility.
即全世界的镇压政府...
that repressive governments around the world...
那 我们还需要复核有关分割的任何条款吗
So, do we need to review any of the terms of the settlement?
不用了
No.
都很清楚
It's all pretty clear.
我真希望你接受她第一次的条件
I really wish you'd taken her first offer.
我知道
I know.
好了
All right, well.
请你往后退一点 不想伤到你
Just step back a little. Don't want you to get hurt.
呃
Um.
请尽可能写大一点
As large as you can, please.
这里天气是不错的
Nice weather down here.
奥马哈变得非常冷
Turned real cold back in Omaha.
是啊
Uh-huh.
刮寒风
Wind chill.
嘿 保罗
Hey, Paul.
伙计 谢谢你 你说得对
Thanks, man, you were right.
提高显示屏真的有用
Raising my monitor really did the trick.
我的脖子感觉好多了 胳膊也没有刺痛感了
My neck feels better, there's no more tingling in my arm.
要不是你我永远不会想到这有什么联系
I would've never made the connection.
太好了 我真的很高兴能帮上忙
That's great, I'm really glad I could help.
感谢致电Land’s End
Thank you for calling Land's End.
我是保罗 今天有什么可以帮你的？
My name is Paul, how can I help you today?
又见面了 保罗
Ciao, bello.
嗨 卡罗
Hi, Carol.
嘿 伙计
Hey, pal.
脸怎么这么长 嗯？
Why the long face? Huh?
看看你周围 生活多美好
Look around you, buddy. Life is good.
这是个错误 戴夫
I made a mistake, Dave.
我人生中最大的错误 我应该留在那儿
Biggest mistake of my life. Should've stayed where I was.
嘿 嘿 嘿 嘿
Hey, hey, hey, hey.
我知道离婚会打击人的自尊心
Look, I know divorce can put a dent in anyone's self-esteem.
奥德丽对你做的事也太过分了
And what Audrey did to you was beyond the pale.
我是说 我讨厌她
I mean, I hate her.
我 我几乎不认识她
I-I barely know her.
你也许不恨她 但我恨死她了
You may not hate her, but I hate her guts.
你只需要重整旗鼓
You, you just gotta get back in the saddle, that's all.
嗯 也许未来的某一天吧
Ah, maybe someday.
如果你想听听我的建议
If you want my advice,
单身母亲应该适合你
single moms is the way to go.
她们把孩子什么的完全从人生中排除了
Yeah, they got the whole kid thing out of their system,
她们只想轰趴 寻欢作乐
and they just wanna party
不 我很好 我--
No, that's okay, I'm--
如果你不想建立情感联系
And if you don't want an emotional connection, which
也是可以理解的 你只需要 呃
understandable, you just uh
我们有各种各样的办法能让你在这玩得愉快
well, we have all sorts of ways you can have a good time down here.
不需要任何附加条件
No strings attached.
- 只要把帐记在旧信用卡上就好 - 不了 我很好
-Just put it on the old credit card. -No, I'm good.
- 真的吗 - 是的
-Really. -Okay, yeah.
实际上 我已经开始和某人约会了
In fact, I started seeing someone.
哦 真的吗？
Oh, yeah?
她其实也是个单身母亲
Single mom, actually.
嗯 现在我们说到一起了 真为你高兴
Mm-hmm, now we're talkin'. Good for you.
保罗 这个真好吃
Paul, this is so good.
谢谢
Thanks.
食谱上要求用山萝卜 但是
The recipe called for chervil, but
现在这个地方还没有山萝卜
you can't get chervil here yet.
- 所以 我用的小茴香 - 嗯
-So, I used dill. -Hm.
不管用的是什么 真的超级好吃
Well, whatever it is, it's super-yummy.
只是个小问题
It's the little things, you know?
我是说 这里除了没有鸟和昆虫
I mean, except for there being no birds or insects,
你会认为自己还在一个正常的世界
you'd think you're in the normal world
然后发生了一些事
and then somethin' happens
你才意识到这里并不是正常世界
and you realize we're not.
我是说 不是要用小茴香替代山萝卜的不正常
I mean, not that substituting dill for chervil
当然这不是个大事 但你懂我的意思
is that big a thing, but you know what I mean.
就像上个月
Like last month,
我父母来看我和乔纳
my parents came down to visit Jonah and me--
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
整个过程用的携带箱
and it's like this whole production
当然乔纳吓坏了
with the carrying boxes, and of course Jonah gets freaked out
以为祖父祖母变得那么巨大可怕
by Grandma and Grandpa being so huge and scary.
嗯
Mm.
一天晚上他们带我们去弗莱明吃晚饭
One night they took us out for dinner at Fleming's,
- 你知道的 很棒 - 嗯哼
-you know, real nice, -Mm-hmm.
乔纳和我坐在桌子上
and Jonah and are sitting on the table
那种特殊的椅子
in those special seats.
然后大的人们不停地看我们
And the big people wouldn't stop staring at us.
另外 这家餐馆吹嘘小人们有多么受欢迎
Plus, the restaurant brags about how small people are welcome,
然而他们却收取了高额的“最低费用”
and then they charge a huge minimum.
他们应该向大人们额外收费
They should charge big people extra.
他们才是拖累这个世界的人
They're the ones dragging down the world.
我知道
I know.
大人们看我们的样子就像我们是怪物一样
Big people look at us like we're freaks.
他们才是怪物
They're the freaks.
哦对了 你有没有听说在南极洲释放了大量的气体？
Oh, did you hear about all that gas being released in Antarctica?
好像是从冰上？释放沼气？
From the ice? The methane?
喔 最近我没有好好看新闻
Oh, I haven't really been following the news that much lately.
很明显这是个大事
Apparently it's a big deal.
科学家说冰融化得越多
Scientists are saying the more the ice melts,
会有更多的沼气泄出使更多的冰融化
the more methane comes out making more ice melt.
看来我们已经过了崩溃的临界点
Apparently we're already way beyond the tipping--
是我楼上的邻居
It's my upstairs neighbor.
好吧 这是最奇怪的事 我-这里几个月都没有这种声音
Well, it's the strangest thing, I-there wasn't a peep for months
我从来没想过他在那--
I don't even think he was here--
然后有一天 突然就
and then suddenly, it's
聚会 聚会 聚会
party, party, party.
几天前我不得不叫安保过来
I had to call security the other night.
杜赞！
Dusan!
嘿 杜赞！
Hey, Dusan!
杜赞！
Dusan!
怎么了？
Yes?
你介意音量调小一点吗？
You mind turning down the music?
我这边想过一个安静的夜晚
I'm trying to have a quiet evening down here.
你好 我的朋友
Hello, my friend.
你好 杜赞
Hello, Dusan.
我可以进来吗？
May I come in?
当然
Certainly.
听着 皮特
So, listen, Pete,
保罗
Paul.
- 保罗 - 保罗
-Paul. -Paul.
这是克里斯汀
And Kristen.
- 啊 你好 克里斯汀 - 嗨
-Ah, hello, Kristen. -Hi.
很抱歉打扰了你们美好的晚餐
I'm sorry I'm disturbing your nice little dinner.
听着…
Listen...
正如我所说 保罗
as I was saying, Paul,
今晚我那边还有一个
I'm having one more, you know,
小聚会要举办
little party at my place tonight.
不想上次那个规模那么大 非常小
Not big like last time. Very small.
只邀请几个亲近的朋友
Just a few close friends.
不是吧！
No!
那是一朵玫瑰？
Is that a rose?
- 是的 - 一朵真正的玫瑰？
-Yeah. -A real rose?
你从哪儿弄来的？
Where'd you get a real rose?
是一家新开的店 呃 全尺寸鲜花集市
It's a new store, uh, Full-Sized Flower Mart.
这朵要多少钱?
How much they're charging for this?
杜赞！
Dusan!
什么 亲爱的?
Quoi, ma Cherie?
你在下面做什么呢？
What are you doing down there?
是的 亲爱的 我来了
Oui, ma Cherie. J'arrive.
不管怎样
Anyway,
我是说
as I was saying,
保罗 如果今晚噪声打扰到你
Paul, if tonight noise disturbs you,
直接上来跟我讲
just come upstairs talk to me.
不用像刚才那样大肆宣扬
Don't make big show like last time,
像个疯子一样大喊大叫
yelling like crazy man.
我们是邻居 邻居就是朋友
We're neighbors. Neighbors are friends.
最好是什么呢 直接参加聚会吧
What's better even, come to the party.
谢谢 不过就像我刚才说的
Thanks, but like I said, we
我们只想安静地吃个晚饭
just want to have a quiet dinner.
尽量声音小点 好吗？
Just try to keep it down, okay?
是 亲爱的 当然
Yes, darling, of course.
嘘 嘘
Shh, shh.
嘘
Shh.
噢
Oh.
真是个愉快的晚上
Thanks for a really nice time.
谢谢你的烹饪和所做的一切
Plus the cooking and all.
抱歉我必须这么早走 临时保姆在家 所以…
Sorry I have to leave so early, but you know, the sitter...
没事 没事
Yeah, yeah. No...
我…
I was...
再上一层
Up one floor.
什么?
What?
是的 还有一层
Yeah, one more.
-谢谢 -噢 谢谢你 伙计
-Gracias -Oh, gracias, tio.
好了 呃
Anyway, uh,
我在想 呃 周末我们可以带上乔纳
I was hoping uh, Sunday we could bring Jonah.
我…我很想见见他
I... I'd love to meet him.
是啊…也许吧
Yeah...maybe.
- 有什么问题吗？ - 不
-Something wrong? -No.
你是个好人 保罗
You're a wonderful guy, Paul.
我真的很高兴和你在一起
And I really enjoy hanging out with you.
嗯哼
Uh-huh.
但是 老实说
But, if I'm honest about how I'm feeling,
我只是觉得 也许 呃 对我来说有点太快了
I just-it might be uh-- it might be too soon for me.
没关系 我明白了
It's fine, I get it.
- 不 我不是那个意思… - 我明白了 没关系
-No, no... -I get it. No, it's fine.
我只是说如果我们带上乔纳的话…
I just mean if we're bringing Jonah into it...
晚安
Have a nice night.
不 我…
No, I...
保罗！
Paul!
玫瑰！
A rose!
保罗！
Paul!
你来了
You come.
你还带了玫瑰
And you bring the rose.
- 这是谢罪礼 - 噢
-It's a peace offering. -Oh.
伙计们
Look, everyone.
这位是保罗 我的邻居
This is Paul, my neighbor.
看看他给我带了什么
And look at what he brings me.
他妈的真的玫瑰！
A real fucking rose!
你觉得这帮忘恩负义的狗娘养的货们
You think any of these other ungrateful sons of bitches
会想得起来带点东西给我吗？
think to bring something to Dusan?
不会 你是唯一一个
No. You're the only one.
我喜欢你
I like you.
我知道我说过这只是一个小聚会
But, I know I said it's only little party,
我只给两三个最亲密的朋友打了电话
but I make two, three phone calls to very close friends,
但是看看发生了什么
look what happens.
所有人都来了
Everybody comes.
这个该死的城市10点之后就无事可做
There's nothing else to do in this fucking city after 10 o'clock.
现在 这是我不明白的
Now, this I do not understand.
好像没有很多人在早上工作
It's not as if so many people have work in the morning.
这是身为小人最坏的一点
You know, this is worst trait about small people--
他们太懒
they're lazy.
不是所有人 但是懒
Not all, not all. But lazy.
就像…这个懒惰的混蛋
Like...this lazy son of a bitch.
康拉德！
Konrad!
你说我什么呢？
What's that you're saying about me?
你扯什么谎呢？
What lies are you telling?
只是在这个小世界没有人想工作
Just that in small world no one wants to work.
你还想指望什么？
What did you expect?
变小是一件美妙的事
It's the wonderful thing about becoming small.
因为你会立即变富
Because you're immediately rich.
除非你太穷了
Unless you're very poor.
那你就只是小
Then you're just small.
康拉德是一个船长
Konrad's a sea captain.
哦？
Oh?
从来没有离他的船超过十米远
Never more than ten meters away from his boat.
哦
Oh.
我真的爱我的船
I do like my boat.
她就在那儿
There she is.
索尼娅 我的美人
Sonja, my beauty.
我家世代是船长
You see, I'm from many generations.
回溯到我爷爷 我爸爸
All the way back to my grandfathers, my father--
都是船长
all sea captains.
所以是什么把你带到Leisureland？
So, what brings you to Leisureland?
杜赞
Dusan.
他甚至说服我变小
He even convinced me to become small,
主要为了女人和聚会
mostly for the women and the parties.
坦白说 我老婆拿着所有的钱
And, frankly, my wife had all the money,
她离开之后 事情变得有点棘手
and after she left, things became a bit tricky.
噢 我懂你
Oh, I can relate.
变小的生活相当不错 你不这么认为吗？
It's quite wonderful to be small, don't you think?
我只能说有好处有坏处
I'd say it has its pluses and minuses.
下个星期我要去塞舌尔
Next week I'll be in the Seychelles,
然后再过两星期 我将
and two weeks after that, I'll be
和朋友们在提提卡卡湖航行一个月
sailing with friends for a month on Lake Titicaca.
你相信吗？我从来没去过提提卡卡湖
Can you believe I've never been to Lake Titicaca?
好吧 但是船是怎么往返的呢？
Well, how does the boat get from place to place?
我是说 你又不能开船
I mean, you can't sail it.
用联邦快递运输 亲爱的老弟
FedEx, my dear boy.
索尼娅航行的速度比我快
Sonja travels faster than I do.
你是怎么弄到一把迷你尺寸的大键琴的？
How'd you get a tiny harpsichord down here?
嗯 没有-- 我必须把它养大
Well, I didn't--I had to have it raised.
怎么做？
Well, how?
打扰一下 那位是谁？
Excuse me, who is that?
- 那边的是谁？ - 嗯？
-Who's that? -Yeah.
那是小罗尼
That's little Ronni.
那是小罗尼？
That's little Ronni?
- 第一个出生的小婴儿 - 是啊
-The first small baby ever born. -Yeah.
- 回到挪威了？ - 天啦噜
-Back in Norway? -Shit.
- 那是小罗尼 - 是的
-That's little Ronni. -Yeah.
你该过去跟他说说话
You should go talk to him.
不好意思 呃…
Sorry, uh...
抱歉 打扰一下
Sorry, excuse me, um,
你-你真的是小罗尼？
is it-is it true you're little Ronni?
是啊 也许没那么小了
Well, maybe not so little anymore.
但是 是我
But yeah, it's me.
哇哦 真是…！
Wow, that's...!
你介意一起拍张自拍吗？
Do you thi-hey-would it be cool to get a selfie?
- 没问题 来这里 - 太棒了
-Yeah, man, get in here. -Awesome.
非常感谢你 我真的很感激
Thank you so much, I really appreciate it.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 来这儿 -哇噢
-Get in here. -Wow.
谢谢 你也是
Thank you, so are you.
这是什么？
What is that?
不 我要知道这是什么 我-我有过敏症
No, I need to know. I-I have allergies.
等等！等等
Wait! Wait.
好吧
Okay.
? De Granada a Casablanca ?
? Enterré mi fantasía ?
? Una guitarra, y un gitano canta ?
? Canta mi Andalucía ?
我要把鞋脱了
I'm gonna take off my shoes.
玩的开心吗？
Having fun?
受够这该死的门铃了
Enough with the fucking doorbell.
早 杜赞先生 我们来做清洁
Good morning, Mr. Dusan. We come clean for you.
昨晚你玩的尽兴 对吗？
So you had fun last night, yeah?
你不知道有个我这么给力的邻居
You didn't know you were so lucky
是个多幸运的事
to have exciting neighbor such as me.
我从来没参加过这样的聚会
Well, I've never been to a party like that.
我从来没-那里有这么多欧洲人
I've nev-there were so many Europeans.
你知道小罗尼昨天也在吗？我是说…
Did you know little Ronni was here? I mean...
- 他可是历史性的人物 -也是个无聊的人
-he is historic. -And boring, you know.
英俊的挪威傻瓜
Good-looking dumb Norwegian guy
走遍世界和所有人做爱--
goes around the world having sex with everyone--
女人 男人 双性人 狗 山羊 猴子
women, men, hermaphrodites, dogs, goats, monkeys.
他早晚会是第一个死于梅毒的小人儿
He'll be the first small baby to die of syphilis,
但还是…历史性的人物
but... historic.
嗯哼 显然他仍然住在原来的殖民地 你知道的地方
Well, apparently he still lives in the original colony, you know,
在挪威 我一直想去看看
over in Norway. I've always wanted to see that.
那里还好吧
It's all right.
你去过？
You've been there?
对啊 我每年都去一两次
Yeah, I go once or twice a year.
康拉德也是 我们在那里做生意
Konrad too. We make business there.
很好的生意
Very good business.
我一定有机会要去看看 我--
Must be somethin' to see. I--
那地方在网上连图片都查不到 你懂的
You know, you can't even get pictures of it online?
没错 我的朋友
Yes, my friend.
这个世界到处是可看的
The world is filled with things to see.
你猜怎么着 我不了解你 保罗
You know, I don't know you, Paul
但是我喜欢你 非常喜欢
but I like you, I like you very much.
我的建议是
And my advice is
从这个令人作呕的破烂小公寓搬出去
get out of this disgusting little fucking apartment
睁大你的眼睛
and open your eyes.
别那么像个美国人
Don't be so American.
你是个好人 保罗
You're nice guy, Paul,
但是有点小可怜
but little bit pathetic guy.
昨晚你又跳又笑
Last night you dance, you laugh
但是在那里面你哭了
but inside you cry.
谁跟你这么说的？
Who are you to talk to me that way?
我是杜赞·米尔科维奇 你的邻居
I'm Dusan Mirkovic, your neighbor.
邻居就是朋友
Neighbors are friends.
朋友只给朋友说实话
Friends tell friends the truth.
没错 也许有时我有那么一点点混蛋
Okay, maybe sometimes I'm a little bit asshole,
但这个世界需要混蛋
but the world needs assholes.
不然垃圾何处可去？
Otherwise where would shit go out.
杜赞…
Dusan...
- 拜拜 - 谢谢你
-Bye. -Thank you.
当我看到大人们变小
When I think of big people becoming small
- 嗯 - 这世上出现了很多
-Mm-mm. -all the new small cities
新的小城市 我就看到了机会
in the world, I see opportunity.
我扪心自问 杜赞
I ask myself, Dusan,
为什么人们想要变小？
why the people they want to become small?
为了帮助保护环境？
To help the environment?
拜托
Please.
他们变小是为了得到物质
The become small to have the things
那些至今为止只属于富人的东西
which until now were only for the rich,
顺便说一下 这真是个天才的设想
which, by the way, is the genius of the concept.
所以我找我兄弟斯尔詹谈了谈--我们在一起工作
So I say to my brother Srdjan-- I work with my brother.
他依然是个大人
He's still big.
顺便 我妻子也是
My wife, too, by the way.
我说
I say,
为什么不把特殊品
why not bring very special items,
奢侈品 带给小顾客呢？
luxury items, to the small consumer?
那些东西从来没人想到要去带
The-The things that nobody else is thinking to bring?
比方说？
Such as?
科伊巴 Esplendido
Well, Cohiba Esplendido.
古巴产 世界上最顶级的雪茄
Cuba. Best cigar in the world.
当你是个大人时要花多少钱买？
How much you pay for this when you big?
45到50美金
Forty-five, fifty dollars.
变小之后 我卖你这雪茄
When you small, I sell you this cigar
只要一美元
for one dollar.
用一支科伊巴 我们能制造2000支小号雪茄
And from this one Cohiba, we make about 2,000 cigars.
好吧 也许它们不是古巴产的
Okay, maybe they're not actually made in Cuba.
也许它们是在布亚诺瓦茨的小阿尔巴尼亚卷出来的
Maybe they're rolled by little Albanians in Bujanovac
但是谁在乎？
but who cares?
而这只是一件东西
And this is just one thing.
还有香水 古龙水 白兰地 波尔图葡萄酒 诺曼底果酒
There's perfume, cologne, brandy, port, Calvados,
松露 鱼子酱 等等
truffles, caviar, pfft.
这些都是合法的吗？
Is all that legal?
宝贝 这里可是狂野西部
Baby, this is Wild West.
谁有时间追踪
Who has time chasing after some
他妈的五英寸高的塞尔维亚人
fucking Serbian guy five inches tall
就为了一些雪茄和酒
over a few cigars and some wine.
我和我兄弟现在遍布在世界各地的
My brother and I are now in seven small cities
七个小城市 七个
around the world. Seven.
保罗 听着 不管你想要什么 我都可以给你
And Paul, listen, anything you want, I can get for you.
任何东西 随时随地
Anything, anytime.
恕我失陪一下
Excuse me a minute.
哈喽？
Hello?
呃 我能跟你聊聊吗？
Uh, can I talk to you for a minute?
Na-pro-shien. 这是干嘛用的？
Na-pro-shien. What this do?
呃 萘普生 用于消炎的
Uh, Naproxen. I-It's a anti-inflammatory.
缓解疼痛和肿胀
It's for pain and swelling.
那这个呢 是干嘛用的？
And this one, what this one do?
这个 维柯丁 也是一种止痛药
Uh, well, Vicodin. That's also a pain killer,
不过…这个用起来要非常小心
but...you wanna be really careful with that one.
止痛药？止痛药好啊
Pain killer? Pain killer good.
听着 我 这不是我的公寓 所以 呃
Listen, I-- this is not my apartment and, uh,
你知道的 我相信你可能经历很多痛苦 但
you know, I'm sure you're probably in a lot of pain, but
你不该偷这些药的
y-you shouldn't steal pills.
我不是在偷
I no steal.
他们过期了 不好
They too old, no good.
杜赞先生 他说我可以拿东西
Mr. Dusan, he say me okay I take away things.
药是为了有病的朋友
Pill for sick friend.
好了 我完工了 浴室打扫干净了
Okay, I finish now. Bathroom clean.
好吧 你朋友怎么了
Well, whatever's wrong with your friend,
看得出来你的脚恢复地并不好
I can see that you have a really, really bad prosthetic foot
而且我确定这会导致你右臀和右膝盖的疼痛
and I'm sure it's causing you pain in your right hip and knee,
或者是你另一边的膝盖和你的下背
probably your other knee, your lower-back.
你怎么知道这些的？
How you know this thing?
你的医生？
You doctor?
职业理疗师
Occupational therapist.
等等
Wait a minute.
我认识你
I-I know you.
你是---天哪
You're the--oh, my God.
你是多年前那个女人
You're that woman from a couple of years ago,
那个异议者
the dissident.
从泰国或哪里来的？你叫啥名啊？
From Thailand or something? What's your name?
陈玉兰 越南来的
Tran Ngoc Lan. Vietnam.
越南来的陈玉兰
Tran Ngoc Lan from Vietnam.
没错
Yes! that's right.
我记得你--你
that's--and I remember that you-you
失去了你的小腿
lost your leg below the knee.
那--那是你！
that's-that- that's you!
哇！
Wow!
啊 杜赞!
Uh, Dusan!
嗨 你知道这是谁吗？
Hey! Do you know who this is here?
当然了 着名的陈玉兰
Of course, the famous Ngoc Lan Tran.
奇迹般地逃离了越南监狱
Dramatic escape from Vietnamese prison,
几近丧命 所以现在 她可以为我打扫房间
almost died, so now, she can clean my house.
美国 充满机会的大陆
America, big land of opportunity.
抬腿 再抬 抬抬抬
Push up, push again. Push, push, push.
好的 再提一下脚后跟
Okay, that's--now take your heel back towards you.
这会更有难度一些
Even harder if you can.
好
Even--yeah.
Yeah.
你把手放在这里 然后……
You-you put your hand right here, now--
静心感受 听见碎裂声了吗？
Feel that. Okay. See that crunching?
你听见了吗？是啊 这是关节炎
You hear it? Yeah, that's arthritis.
这已经…很糟糕了
That's already...pretty bad.
保罗
Paul,
你真是充满了惊喜
you're full of surprises.
你会这么多却做不好接电话的工作？
You can do this but you work shit job answering phones?
我下调至这里的时候 我没想到我会来这工作
Well, when I moved down here, I didn't think I'd be working
所以 我任由我的执照到期了而且…
so I let my license expire and...
现在 我不得不从零开始
now, I'd have to get it in a whole 'nother state.
这真是…太没劲了
It's a whole...it's a boring story.
我不想这么说 但是…
I hate to say it, but...
如果你不立刻找点事做
if you don't do something pretty soon,
你就会需要一个新的膝盖了
you're gonna need a new knee.
或者一个新的屁股
Maybe even a new hip.
你需要去找专家看看
You gotta go to a specialist as soon as you can
然后换一个新的脚
a-and get a whole new foot.
同时呢
In the meantime,
我可以对假肢训练做些调整
I could make some adjustments on the existing prosthetic.
然后我或许可以给你一些可以更好行走的建议
And maybe give you some pointers on how to walk better.
我只是不想看你毫无意义地受这些罪
I just hate to see you needlessly suffer
在你经历了这么多之后
after all you've been through.
好了 我完事了 跟我来
Okay. I finish work you come with me.
啊 不了 我拿到我的工具了 我可以在这里把它完成
Yeah, no, I can get my tools, I can do it right here.
不 我说的是之前提到的生病的朋友 需要药
No. I say you before my friend sick, need pill.
你和我来家里 帮助她
You come with me my house. Help her.
你帮助她
You help her.
我不确定我能…我能帮你
I...I don't think I was clear. I can help you with this
但我不是个医生 所以
but I'm not a doctor, so
你的朋友 她怎么了？
your friend, whatever's wrong with her,
她需要去诊所或者医院…
she's gotta go to a clinic or a hospital...
不！诊所不好
No! Clinic no good.
我带她去诊所等了很长时间
I bring her clinic wait too long time.
但那些蠢货医生说的都是些废话
Stupid doctor say no help for her, no do nothing.
他在大世界里是个蠢医生 现在他变小了
He no good stupid doctor in big world, now he small.
和我来
You come with me.
快和我来
You come with me now.
呃
Uh.
来
Come.
你住在附近？
You live near here?
不 还挺远的
No, still far.
或许我们可以打个车
Maybe we should grab a car.
不需要 坐公交即可
No need car. Take bus.
冒昧问一句
If-If you don't mind my asking,
你前几年挺有名的
you were so famous a couple of years ago,
我是说 所有人都在谈论你
I mean, everybody was talking about you.
我只是觉得你可能曾经
I just would've thought you'd have been
发表演讲或是着书立说
giving speeches or writing books.
你怎么会沦落到给别人做清洁工的地步？
How'd-How'd you wind up cleaning houses?
为了生计
Need money for live.
在上电视之后 我呆在医院几乎死了
After TV box, I stay hospital so long time, almost die.
然后辗转在三个寄宿家庭 但是问题层出不穷
Then three host family, but too much problems.
休闲岛的人们太自私了
Leisureland people too selfish.
我独自一人反而好些 赚钱吃饭 十分简单
Better I live only me, work job make money, easy.
嗨 你！
Hey, you!
来 来啊！
Come, come!
晚安
Buenas noches.
哟！
Yo!
来啊
Come on.
没时间做梦了
No time for baby dreams.
我能问问要去几层么？
Can I ask how high we're going?
七层 ---七层？
-Seven floor. -Seven?
好吧 我们能坐电梯吗？
Well, can we use the elevator?
没有电梯
No elevator.
你好 贝妮塔 最近咋样啊？
Hola Benita, Como esta?
你好
Hola.
穿上鞋
Take the shoe.
你好 格拉迪斯！
Hola Gladys!
这位女士 格拉迪斯 是我的朋友
This lady Gladys. Gladys my friend.
她病得很重
She very sick.
格拉迪斯 你感觉咋样啊？
Gladys, how you feel?
你怎么样？
?Cómo está?
我给你带来了点吃的
I bring food for you.
我带来了医生 他是医生
I bring doctor. This man doctor.
男医生
Hombre médico.
医生
Médico.
格拉迪斯女士孤苦无依
This lady Gladys alone, no have nobody.
他们变小时她的丈夫死在了墨西哥
Husband die Mexico when they make small.
蠢货们忘了把金牙拔出来了
Stupid people forget take the gold from the teeth,
头爆炸了
head explode.
啥？
What?
她丈夫爆炸了
Husband head explode.
头部爆炸了 从牙齿那
Head explode. From teeth.
她来这里无钱无友
She come alone, no money.
我在第一个寄宿家庭里遇见的她
I meet her she housekeeper first host family,
一个富有的休闲域者
rich Leisureland people.
现在她病了 丢了工作
Now she sick, no more work.
所以你在照顾她
Okay you take care for her.
我为她做不了什么
I can't do anything for her.
这个女人真的病了
That woman is really sick.
看起来可能要死了
Looks like she might die.
她是要死了
Oh yeah she die soon.
癌症 充满了胃部
Cancer. Cancer all over stomach.
我会陪着她的
I be with her she die.
独自死亡真的很不好
Most bad thing die alone.
来吧 有点医德
Come on, be like doctor.
让她感觉好点
Make her feel good.
你好
Hola Se?ora.
哪儿疼？
Where does it hurt?
哪儿都疼
Everything hurts.
我活不长了
I do not have much time left in my life.
哪种药对他最好？
Which pill most good for her?
我不知道
I have no idea.
你一定知道什么
But you know thing.
哪种药最有效？
Which pill most strong?
复方羟可酮
Percocet.
是的 复方羟可酮 非常好的止痛药
Yes, Percocet. Very good for pain.
吃多少--两片四片还是五片？吃多少啊？
How much--two, four, five? How much?
两片吧
Try two.
两片？她病地很重
Two? This lady very sick.
药过期了
Pill old.
那四片吧
We give four.
这些是止痛的
These are for the pain.
谢了 大夫
Gracias, doctor.
你试过每隔几个小时帮她翻翻身吗？
Have you tried to move her every couple of hours
所以她没有褥疮？
so she doesn't get bedsores?
我们会这么做的
We should probably do that.
来吧 来---好的
Come, there you--okay.
看？你的确知道些什么
See? You know thing.
谢谢你 杜赞先生的朋友 谢谢你帮了格拉迪斯
Thank you Mr. Dusan friend. You help Gladys good.
没事
Okay. Well.
让我们做些矫正吧
Let's make those adjustments.
如果你想提起你的脚的话
If you just wanna slip off your foot.
不 不做脚了 我累了
No, no foot. I tired.
你走吧 我陪着格拉迪斯
You go away. I stay with Gladys.
快走吧
You go away now.
真的？我是说--
Really? I mean--
我累了 你走吧
I tired. You go away.
好吧
Okay.
改天再说吧
Some other time, I guess.
我只是不知道我啥时候能再见到你
I just-I just don't know when I'm gonna see you again.
周四 你周四来 好吧？
Thursday. You come Thursday, okay?
周四早上你来治腿
Thursday morning you come fix leg.
十点钟
Ten o'clock.
周四十点钟
Thursday at ten o'clock.
对了 我叫保罗
My name's Paul, by the way.
保罗 萨弗兰内克
Paul Safranek.
我看看
Let's see...
冰川中有很多可用的
The Extra Large is available in glacier,
卵石,郁金香,辣椒、苔藓和茄子
pebble, tulip, cayenne, moss and aubergine.
辣椒 红的吗？
Cayenne, is-is that like red?
棕红色的 像砖块一样
It's-It's a brownish red. It's more like brick.
不 我不喜欢砖头
No, I don't like brick.
你不认为苔藓很可爱吗？
Do you think moss is pretty?
呃-我不知道 女士
You know, I-I don't know, lady.
你为什么不随便挑个颜色呢？
Why don't you just pick a color please?
别敷衍我
Don't be short with me.
你说啥？
What did you say?
鞋
Shoe.
格拉迪斯呢？
Where's Gladys?
哦 她死了
Oh, she die.
哦 不…
No. oh...
我很遗憾
I'm so sorry.
我觉得我可能给她的药太多了
I think maybe I give her too much pill.
不管怎样 她死得很安详
Anyway, she die very happy smiling.
好吧 你来治脚吧
Okay, you fix foot now.
快点
You do quick.
我一小时之后就要打扫房子
Must clean house soon. One hour.
快点
You do quick.
快啊
Quick!
哦 谢谢你 非常好
Oh, thank you, very nice.
快点完事 我很忙的
You finish soon okay? I very busy.
我快到了
I'm gettin' there.
我猜你喜欢蝴蝶
I guess you like butterflies.
蝴蝶
Butterflies.
是啊 我很喜欢
Yes I like very much.
当我是个小女孩时
When I little girl
我爸爸带我和我姐姐去看蝴蝶
my father he take me my sister go see butterfly.
他们住在我们村旁的树上
Near my village they live in a tree.
你知道
You know,
他们每年从寒冷的地方飞去温暖的地方
they fly cold place to hot place every year.
冬去春又来
Stay tree then go away come back.
呃 迁徙的蝴蝶
The uh, migrating butterflies.
是啊 -对 听起来很美
-Yes. -Yeah, sounds beautiful.
用越南语蝴蝶怎么说？
How do you say butterfly in Vietnamese?
蝴蝶
Con bu'ó'm.
胡爹
Kon booyem?
蝴蝶
Con bu'ó'm.
胡爹
Kon booyem.
你想念你的村庄了吗？
You miss your village?
没有村庄了
No more village.
政府把人民迁移来蓄水
Government make the people go away put water
哪里都是水 太多的水了
all over, all over everywhere. Too much water.
太多的水？
Too much water?
水用来发电
Big water for make electricity.
哦 水坝啊
Oh, a dam.
对 水坝 他们建水坝--水坝 呃呃
-Yes, dam. They make dam. -Dam. Uh-huh.
很多村庄都没了
Many village no more.
这就是为什么我进监狱了
That's why I go prison.
我和我姐姐参与了抗议
Me my sister make protest.
大规模的抗议--呃呃
-Big protest. -Uh-huh.
那 你姐姐现在在哪？
Well, where's your sister now?
她死在监狱里了
She die prison.
太冷了 胸部坏死了 她死了
Too cold. Chest fill up bad. She die.
发生啥了？-没啥
-What happen? -Nothin'.
不 就是…给我点时间 就是…
No, just, no... give me a minute, just--
你做了什么？-没有 没啥 就是…
-What you do? -No, nothing, nothing, I just--
你这个傻瓜！
You stupid man!
无论如何 你现在需要一个新脚了 我们会给你一个好的
You needed a new foot anyway. We'll get you a good one.
这很难理解吗？耶稣！
Is that so hard to understand? Jesus!
别侮辱耶稣！
Don't say Jesus bad way!
啥 你现在还纠结我的用词？
What, now I'm supposed to watch my language?
你比我妈妈还糟糕
You're worse than my mother.
我为你妈妈感到遗憾
I feel sorry for your mother.
我确定她很为你的错误而头疼
I sure she suffer too much for your fault.
别这么快！
Not do so fast!
真空吸尘器很好用
Vacuum cleaner need time same direction clean good.
好吧 你可以拿走
Yeah, and you can take these,
这是几天前送来的三角饺
these are samosas from a couple of days ago.
谢谢 我收下了
Thank you, yes. I take all these.
哦 这是芝士大力菜-
Oh, I think this is saag paneer--
这可能有点过期了
might be a little bit old.
哦 在监狱里这可是难得的佳肴啊
Oh, in prison we die for such food.
好吧 今天没多少剩菜
Okay, not too many leftover entrees today
但我放了好些烤土豆汤
but I threw in lots of baked potato soup.
谢谢你 罗杰
Thank you, Roger.
这边请
There you go.
嗨 玉兰 终于给你自己找到一个帮手哈？
Hey, finally got yourself a helper, huh, Ngoc Lan?
这是保罗 他伤的我的脚
This Paul. He break my foot.
你要怎么处理这些啊 老铁？
How'd you manage that, buddy?
说来话长 我们正在想辙
It's a long story, we're sorting it out.
他是个笨蛋！
He stupid!
你好 卡德纳斯
Hola, Se?or Cárdenas.
饿么？
?Hambre?
恩 格莱西亚
Ay, sí, chinita. Gracias.
上帝会赐福你的
God will repay you.
你的肺咋样？
How's your lung?
我感觉好点了
I feel a little better today.
多谢
Gracias.
布埃诺
Bueno.
好的 过来这边
Okay, over here, this way.
淡淡的忧伤 迷情的摇滚？
Mucho dolor, verdad?
是啊 很痛啊
Yes, it hurts a lot.
哦 看起来就很痛
Oh, it looks really painful.
我帮他洗了个澡
I give him baths and scrub him
还用了香草 但然而并没有什么用
and put herbs, but nothing helps.
我觉得这是藓
I bet that's ringworm
我不知道西班牙语怎么说
which I don't know how to say in Spanish.
藓是一种真菌 所以
But ringworm is a fungus, so
你想要它干燥的话
you want it dry.
山高 山高 不 不 阿瓜 阿瓜
Seco. Seco. No ba?o. No ba?o. No agua. No agua.
呃…
And uh...
我去药店碰碰运气看能买到什么
see if I can pick something up at the drugstore
然后明天带回给他
and bring it for him tomorrow.
好的 带来
Yes, you bring.
医药
Ma?ana medicina.
- 医药 -谢谢你 医生
-Ma?ana medicina. -Gracias, doctor.
好了 去看下一个吧
Okay, next. Let's go.
- 谢谢 医生 -谢谢
-Gracias, doctor. -Gracias.
- 我们走！-我来了！
-Let's go! -I'm comin'.
照顾好他
Take care for him.
- 再见 -谢谢
-See you next time. -Gracias.
所以就这样？我们这就回家？
So that's it? We go home now?
我们现在去教堂祷告
Now we go church pray Jesus.
你明天八点来接我
You come back tomorrow pick me up eight o'clock.
好的 我会来的
Yeah, okay, I'll be here.
早上好啊 杜赞先生 我们来为你打扫了
Good morning, Mr. Dusan. We come clean for you.
接电话可难以彰显您的身份
Answering telephones was not dignified enough for you.
所以你现在被提拔去扫厕所了
Now you progress to cleaning toilets.
我爱你 保罗
I love you, Paul.
我真的爱你 你可真有意思
I really love you. You're such a funny guy.
真好玩儿
Hilarious.
像我说的
Like I said,
你真是个好人
you're too much nice guy
也有那么一点可怜
and a little bit...pathetic guy.
到她安个新脚为止
It's just until she gets a new foot.
- 那是啥时候啊 - 不知道呢
-When will that be. -I don't know.
那个医生说要一个月 也可能六个礼拜
The doctor said a month, maybe six weeks.
- 那可得有段时间了 -我知道
-Ah, that's an eternity. -I know.
那这段时她只能用假腿了
Meantime she's stuck with a peg leg,
聊胜于无罢了
which is almost as bad as having nothing at all.
我是说 看看她
I mean, look at her,
现在她像个该死的海盗似的晃来晃去！
she's waddling around like a goddamned pirate!
保罗！别和杜赞先生说话了！
Paul! You no talk with Mr. Dusan!
你和维罗妮卡一起上楼！
You go upstairs with Veronica!
-保罗！-听到了
-Paul! -I heard you.
别担心 保罗
Don't worry, Paul.
杜赞会救你的
Dusan will save you.
哇
Wow.
是啊 陈小姐 都拿走吧
Yeah, Miss Tran, take everything.
康拉得先生和我后天就要走了
Mr. Konrad and I are leaving day after tomorrow
而且不知道我们什么时候回来
and don't know when we'll be back.
好的 谢谢你
Okay good. Thank you.
保罗 杜赞先生说我可以拿走全部食物
Paul, Mr. Dusan say I take all the food.
你帮我找个大箱子
You go find me big box.
马上
In a minute.
不过我得先说一件重要的事情
First there's something very important to discuss.
和我么？
Me?
情况是这样
This is the situation.
我们不知道具体咋回事
I don't know exactly what,
但情况真的是严重很严重
but something big-- very big-
它发生在最初的缩小殖民地里
is happening at the original small colony.
你知道的 挪威的那个
You know, the one in Norway.
他们想让我立即去那里
They want me to go there right away
并带给他们一份非常重要的东西
with a very important delivery.
这件事要解释起来就太复杂了
It's too complicated to explain.
这是机密而且…十分紧急
Top secret and... very urgent.
最重要的是他们许我们以重金
Most important they are offering us very big money.
非常多的钱
Very big.
这意味着我们需要额外的帮助
That means we need extra help
尽快完成这件事 来取悦他们
to do this quickly, make them happy.
而且很遗憾我要这么说 但我们需要同样优秀的帮手
And I'm sorry to say, we need the same excellent helper
就是正在帮你的人
who is currently helping you.
他
Him.
是的 玉兰
That's right, Ngoc Lan,
我必须和他们去挪威
I have to go with these guys to Norway.
所以你是说…
So... you say...
保罗跟你们去挪威？
Paul go with you Norway?
形势所迫
That's the situation.
情况紧急
Emergency situation.
完全出于人道主义
And deeply humanitarian.
我的意思是 玉兰 我会
I mean, Ngoc Lan, I will
安然无恙的回来帮你
be able to help when I get back one-hundred-percent
当新假肢 还有
when the new foot, and--
你们周三就出发？
You leave Wednesday?
是的
Yes.
去多久
And how long you go?
10天 也可能更久
Ten days. Maybe more.
好吧 挪威
Okay, yes, Norway.
我也去
I go Norway too.
不 不 不 你不用跟我们去
No, no, no, not you.
只有保罗去
Only Paul.
我也去
I go Norway too.
保罗 途中你可以帮我
Paul, you help me on the trip.
但你还得在这
But you're very busy here
忙你的人道主义活动
with humanitarian activities on your own.
还有你的清扫生意
And your cleaning business.
维拉妮卡她们对这些一清二楚
Veronica and other ladies know every place.
她们为我做事 我付给他们不错的报酬
They do for me, I pay them good.
没问题 我可以去
No problem I go.
挪威移民邀请了我很多次
Norway colony people invite me so many time
但我还从没去过
but I never go.
我感觉非常 非常愧疚
Feel so, so guilty.
他们人都非常好
They so nice people.
什么情况
What?
谁邀请过你
Who invited you?
在转换过程中受伤后我住院很长时间
When I hospital so long time after TV box,
世界各地的人们
people all over world
送给我贺卡 鲜花 糖果
send me happy card, flower, candy,
让我非常欣慰
make me feel good.
还寄给我很多信
So many letter.
其中一封非常特殊 我印象深刻
One letter very special I never forget.
是乔根·阿斯比恩森寄来的
From Jorgen Asbjornsen.
乔根·阿斯比恩森给你寄过信？
You got a letter from Jorgen Asbjornsen?
阿斯比恩森博士给我写信说
Dr. Asbjornsen write me
他非常内疚
say he feel so, so bad
我因他的失误而蒙难
I suffer for his fault.
他说他很痛苦
He say he painful.
从没想过缩小有如此糟糕的后果
He never think make small so bad for people.
博士的信让我感到非常欣慰
Dr. Asbjornsen letter make me feel so good.
我也给他回信了
I write letter too,
我说现在我第一次感到变小是这么幸福
say now first time I happy be small.
他告诉我任何时候都能到挪威旅行
He say me make trip go Norway any day.
但我太忙了
But I too busy.
一直没时间
Always too busy.
现在上帝给我一份特殊的赏赐 到挪威去
Now Jesus give me special gift, go Norway.
谢谢您 杜赞先生 谢谢您 康拉德先生
Thank you Mr. Dusan, thank you Mr. Konrad.
没错
Yes.
我也去挪威
I go Norway too.
太开心了
So happy.
感谢您给我这次难得的机会
Thank you special time.
保罗 瞧
Paul, look.
这是乔根·阿斯比恩森和他的妻子
This Jorgen Asbjornsen. And his wife.
哦 我的天 乔根·阿斯比恩森
Oh, my God. Jorgen Asbjornsen.
你好
Hello.
太荣幸了
This is such an honor.
是的 没错
I know, I know.
对吧 保罗
See, Paul?
上帝听见了我的祈祷
Jesus smile for me.
我对保罗说过 我去挪威就是为了见您
I say Paul I want visit Norway only for meet you.
没错
It's true.
我是安妮·海琳 你好
-I'm Anne-Helene. -Hello.
来和我们一起坐吧
Please, sit. Join us.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们正与世界擦身而过
We're watching the world go by.
这听起来真不错
Sounds great.
您不知道我们对陈女士的事
You have no idea how terribly
感到多么难过
grief-stricken we were by Miss Tran's case.
乔根因为这项技术导致的失误辗转难眠
Jorgen has lost so much sleep over all the abuses.
这样的景色令人望而生畏 是吧
It's humbling, huh?
大自然真是极富耐心的雕刻家
Nature is such a patient sculptor.
每天雕琢一点
Grinding a tiny bit
每天一点点 历经千年
each day slowly, slowly for thousands of years to
竟雕刻出如此壮美的景色
make such a supremely beautiful thing.
太可惜了
What a waste.
真是太可惜了
What a dreadful waste.
希望你们能原谅乔根
You'll have to excuse Jorgen.
这些日子他真的非常难熬
These past few days has been especially hard.
这样的重大决定做的如此之迅速
Such a big decision to make and so quickly.
通常我们到移民聚集地
Normally when we visit the Colony,
都会在霍宁斯沃格呆几天
we like to spend a few days in Honningsv?g.
但是发生了那件事
But then the news came...
然后 我们就到这了
and uh, yeah, well, here we are
形势所迫
suddenly imposing on you.
我们根本来不及收拾行李
We scarcely had the time to pack.
抱歉 你说的是什么事
I'm sorry, w-what news?
甲烷泄露
Why, the methane release.
在南极 你知道甲烷吧
In Antarctica. You must know about the methane.
知道
Yeah...
这并不新鲜 是吧 我是说
that's not-that's not new, is it? I mean--
不管新鲜不新鲜
New or old,
这就是终点
it's the end.
一切都完了
It's the end of everything.
世界已经经历了5次灭绝
The world has already seen five major extinctions,
这将是第6次
and now there will be another.
我 我也不愿相信
I...I didn't want to believe it.
没人愿意相信 但
None of us did, but
我们在赫尔辛基时 那儿缩小和没缩小的人都在一起
there we were in Helsinki, big and small.
气候学家 细菌学家 人口学家 物理学家
Climatologists, bacteriologists, demographers, physicists,
免疫学家
immunologists,
足足有26名诺贝尔获得者
26 Nobel Prize winners among us.
我们建了无数模型 进行了无数运算
We built all the models, did all the math,
结论都一致
and all conclusion was consistent.
智人将从地球消失
Homo Sapiens will soon vanish from the Earth.
这是万分精确的必然
It is now an actuarial certainty.
无论末日以什么形式来临
No matter how the end will come--
环境灾难
environmental disaster,
流行病爆发
pandemic disease,
令人窒息的空气
unbreathable air,
水源进口 食物不足
impotable water, not enough food,
核冬天 或者几种形式夹杂袭来
nuclear winter, some combination of them all.
与此同时地球本身也将对人类进行净化
Relatively soon the Earth will indeed purge itself of human life,
只有上帝知道会有多少物种受牵连
and God knows how many other species.
你是说真的灭绝吗 缩小不管用吗
Do you really mean extinction? What about downsizing?
嗯 缩小能使灭绝来的晚一些
Yeah, yeah, too little too late.
世界人口只缩小了三分之一
Only three percent of the world has miniaturized.
时间太紧了
There simply isn't enough time.
智人也不算进化非常成功的物种
Not a very successful species, these Homo Sapiens,
尽管拥有高智商
even with such great intelligence.
智人存在短短20万年
Barely 200,000 years.
短嘴鳄却已经存在20亿年了
Alligator has survived 200 million years
凭着只有核桃那么大的脑袋
with a brain the size of a walnut.
上千年来人类从未停止
People have been predicting the end of the world
预测世界末日
for thousands of years.
现在末日真的来了
And now it's really happening.
我猜有人猜对了
I guess somebody had to be right someday.
真遗憾
So sad.
非常遗憾
Very sad.
好了 我去睡了
Okay, I go sleep now.
晚安 保罗
Good night, Paul.
晚安 玉兰
Good night, Ngoc Lan.
哦
Ay.
你没事吧
You okay?
我没事
I fine.
我觉得我应该检查一下你的腿
You know, maybe I should take a look at your leg.
好啊 你来检查吧
Okay, yes, you look.
哦 呀
Oh, yup.
哦
Wow.
木桩擦破了皮
That peg is really making the skin chafe.
嗯
Okay.
你知道吗
You know,
如果十年前有人跟我说
if somebody told me ten years ago
有天我只有5英尺大
that one day I'd be five inches tall,
离了婚
divorced,
还帮一个着名的越南异派做义肢
helping a famous Vietnamese dissident get a new foot
巡游穿越挪威海峡时
while cruising up a fjord in Norway
还和乔根·阿斯比恩森谈论世界末日
discussing the end of the world with Jorgen Asbjornsen,
我肯定认为他疯了
I would've said he was crazy.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
抱歉 我以为
I'm sorry. I-I thought--
天啊 我真蠢
Jesus, I'm such an idiot.
不
No.
没关系
Please.
我想要
I want.
早
Morning.
早上好
Good morning.
那是什么声音
What's that sound?
问候声
A greeting.
哇
Wow!
就是那 那是原来的移民聚集地
That's it, that's the original colony.
等等 这没有防护网也没有隔离墙吗
Wait, and there's no net? No walls?
没有 我们很幸运
No, we've been lucky.
这里蚊子成灾
We are too close to the sea for the mosquitoes.
多年来 我们发现
And over the years, we realized
这儿的鸟儿更喜欢吃旅鼠
that the birds, they preferred the lemmings.
没错 我们就是从这开始的
But yes, this is where we started
很多年前
many years ago.
乔根 你好啊
Jorgen, good to see you.
欢迎
Welcome.
哦 不
No, no.
乔根
Jorgen!
安妮·海琳
Anne-Helene!
哦 你来这儿真是太好了
Oh, thank God you're here!
为什么没人告诉我你来了
Why didn't anyone tell me?
哦 我太爱你了
Oh, I love you so much.
我也爱你们
I love you both so much.
哦 自从做了那个决定以来
Oh, ever since the decision,
你不在这 我就觉得一切都不对
I didn't feel right without you here.
你知道我多担心
And you know how I am when I worry.
吃不下 睡不着
I can't eat. I can't sleep.
这儿的每个人都能为我作证
Ask anyone here, they tell you.
抱歉打扰一下 乔根
Sorry to interrupt, Jorgen,
我们现在急需你的建议
but we need your advice immediately.
好的 抱歉 索尔维格
Yes. Excuse us, Solveig.
没事 亲爱的 你还有要事在身
Of course, darling. You've got important things to do.
哦 杜赞 杜赞 杜赞
Oh! Dusan, Dusan, Dusan!
你这么快就到了真是太好了
Bless you for coming so quickly.
索尔维格 亲爱的 我随时恭候
Solveig, my darling, I'm always happy to help
不管是困境顺境还是幸福时刻
in difficult times, in easy times, in happy times.
我都乐意来拜访你和友好的村民们
Is always a pleasure to come and visit you and your lovely village.
哦 你太好了
Oh, it is lovely, isn't it?
难以想象不能再次见到你
I can't bear to think I won't see it again.
你知道 起初是我建立了
You know, I'm the one who made this colony
这个聚集地
possible in the first place.
我小时候就来过
I've been coming since I was just a baby.
我记得有一次
I remember one time--
等等 我认识你
Wait. I know you.
我昨晚梦见你了
You were in my dream last night.
梦里你是一匹马也许是小马驹 很健壮的那种
You were a horse or a pony-- something very strong.
我骑着你穿越险象环生的森林
And I mounted you and rode you through a dangerous forest.
-是吗 - 现在你来了
-Okay. -And here you are.
在我们离开之前你来了
Right before we leave.
又是一个奇迹
Another miracle.
你是来加入我们的 是吗
You are coming with us, aren't you?
你去哪儿
Where are you going?
去里面
In there.
你想进去看看吗
Would you like to see?
这儿通向哪儿
Where this go?
通向地下
To the vault.
- 地下？ - 没错
-The vault? -Oh, yes.
很早以前我们就开始挖了
We've been working on it almost since the very beginning.
当乔根做出那个伟大的发现时
When Jorgen made his big discovery,
我是说 瞧啊 乔根 你是个天才
I said, look, Jorgen, you're a genius,
缩小是天才的想法 没人质疑这一点
and downsizing is a genius idea. No one is questioning that.
但要是人们不能接受怎么办
But what if people don't accept it?
如果结果并非我们所想？
What if it doesn't come out on time?
不管怎样 这是他们想出来的
Anyway, this is what they came up with.
根据我的建议
On my suggestion.
托瓦兹 我的甜心 带我们的朋友参观一下
Torvald, be a sweetheart and give our friends a little tour.
好的
Well, sure.
这条隧道通向地下
The tunnel leads to a vault
深入地壳1.6千米
1.6 kilometers inside the Earth's lithosphere
由双层因科镍合金625围护
and is encased in a double layer of Inconel 625.
为确保广泛的物种多样性
In addition to maintaining a broad spectrum of biodiversity,
洞穴里备有土层供植物生长
the vault is equipped with fields for growing foods,
有森林提供木材 有牲畜发展畜牧业
forests for lumber, livestock for animal husbandry.
居住区域广阔无边
The residential areas are spacious
供未来多少代人口在此生存都绰绰有余
and easily expandable to provide for future generations.
等等 但是这些不都在地下吧
Wait, but that's not all underground?
没错
Oh, yes!
微缩的身型让我们在地上生存成为可能
Our new small size makes it possible.
否则做梦也别想
Otherwise we never could have dreamed of preserving
在这样一个安全的地方维持这样大的一个世界
so much of the world in a single safe place.
太赞了
This is brilliant.
很赞是吧 就像 就像诺亚方舟
Isn't this brilliant? It's like- It's like Noah's Ark.
没错 简直就是诺亚方舟
Yes. exactly! It's Noah's Ark!
那么 能源是什么 核能吗
So, how-what do you do for power, is it nuclear?
不 不是的 完全使用地热能
No, no, 100% geothermal.
而且我们有相互协作的有机体系
And we have interoperable organic systems
可以人工生产太阳能
to manage production of artificial sunlight,
氧气 消除二氧化碳 净化水源等等
oxygen, CO2 elimination, water purification, and so on.
那你们要在这呆多久
And how long will you stay down there?
托瓦兹 多久 8000年？
Torvald, how long is it? 8,000 years?
嗯 差不多吧
Well, something like that.
直到地球表面环境趋于稳定为止
Just until the surface environment stabilizes.
我们现在做的并非史无前例
It's not unprecedented what we are doing here.
大概100年前
Less than a hundred thousand years ago
人类经历了一次核灭绝
humans underwent a near-extinction.
可能只有2000人得以幸存
Maybe 2,000 survived.
此后由那些人
And from that handful
繁衍出如今数十亿的人类
came all of the billions of people you see today.
所有物种重启 我们做的这些一点也不新鲜
Rebooting the species. It's nothing new.
是的 确实是
Yeah, exactly.
我的朋友们
My friends.
多年前
Many years ago,
当我们发现细胞可以被缩小
when we discovered cellular miniaturization,
这个不断遭遇厄运的世界
the world which had seemed so doomed
突然又充满了无数可能性
felt suddenly so full of possibilities.
直到最近 我仍然希望
So, until very recently, I maintained hope
明天开展的应急计划
that the contingency plan we embark upon tomorrow
依然只是
could remain simply that--
一个计划而已
a plan.
但是
But...
历史被打破了
history has spoken.
这是我们在多年来一直称为家园的地方的
And this is our final dinner in the place we've called home
最后一餐
for so many years.
没错 离开这里固然令人伤心
Yes, we are sad to leave,
离开的缘由也同样令人难过
and terribly sad for the reasons why.
但人类这个物种太美妙了
But man is too beautiful,
是太不可思议的生命形式
too improbable a life form
因而绝不能允许其永远从宇宙消失
to be allowed to disappear forever from the cosmos.
现在
Now then,
我想问一下原聚集地
I would like to ask the surviving members of the
生存下来的人们
original colony to stand.
看看他
Ah, look at him.
小罗尼
Little Ronni.
他是怎样长大成人的
How he has grown.
我再问你们一次
I ask you again
正如我多年前问的那样
as I asked you so many years ago.
一代接一代
Generations to come,
或许整个人类都会感激你们
perhaps all of humanity will thank you
为你们今天的勇气和承诺
for your bravery and commitment.
但你们必须问一问自己
But you must ask yourself
是否真的准备好进入新世界
whether you are truly ready to enter a new world.
因为那儿有去无回
For there will be no turning back.
你们准备好了吗
Are you ready?
我准备好了
I am ready!
- 我准备好了 - 是的
-I am ready! -Yes!
我准备好了
I am ready!
大家准备好了吗
Is everyone ready?
我们准备好了
We are ready!
保罗
Paul!
什么事
Yeah.
你能过来吗？
Can you come down here?
你去哪了？ 我到处找你
Where you go? I look many place for you.
我哪儿也没去
I was just here.
我在这和杜赞先生聊聊 他说那个胖女人付钱了
I talk with Mr. Dusan, he say fat lady pay,
他准备回去了
he ready go back.
我很高兴听你这么说
I happy for that.
我们离开卡德纳斯先生和洛佩兹夫人太久了
Too long time away from Se?or Cardenas and Mrs. Lopez.
恩 我很担心他们
Oh, I worry too much for them.
玉兰 你不能只是
Ngoc Lan, you can't just be
担心千里之外的那小部分人
worried for a few little people thousands of miles away.
你的目光要放远大些
You have to look at the big picture.
你为什么这么说
Why you say like this?
因为 卡德纳斯先生和洛佩兹夫人
Because...Mr. Cardenas and Mrs. Lopez,
他们没机会了
they don't stand a chance,
我们也没有
None of us do.
都结束了
It's over.
你想跟他们一起去
You want go with them.
我希望你也跟我一起
And I want you to come with me.
你简直疯了
You crazy man!
我一直以为你只是蠢 现在我知道你还是个疯子
Always I know you stupid. Now I see you crazy too.
我怎么就是疯子了
How am I crazy?
你听见他们说的话了
You heard them.
这是拯救人类的唯一机会
This is the only chance for the survival of our species--
这太扯了
that's huge!
你想帮忙？
You want to help people?
这就是那些你应该帮助的人
These are the people that you should be helping.
人类的未来就在那洞穴的下面
The future of humanity is down that hole!
你到那儿是去帮谁？
Who you help down there?
这儿的人确实需要帮助但没必要非得到那愚蠢的洞里
People here need help, not down stupid hole!
杜赞先生 康纳德先生
Mr. Dusan, Mr. Konrad,
保罗疯了 和他谈谈吧
talk to crazy Paul.
他想下到洞里 还让我跟他一起去
He want go down hole, me go with him.
保罗 保罗 保罗
Paul, Paul, Paul...
你为什么要做这种蠢事
Why do you want to do such a silly thing?
杜赞 这些人确实在试着做点什么
Dusan, these people are actually trying to do something
拯救人类 我也想这么做
to save the human race. I wanna be a part of that.
好啊 你想帮忙
Okay, fine, you want to help
那就跟我一样 为他们提供精液样本
then do what I did, give them a semen sample.
我也这么做了
I did it too.
极为乐意的提供了帮助
A much more pleasant way to help.
如果我不愿参与这件事
If I'm not supposed to be a part of this thing,
那我在这做什么
then w-what am I doing here?
我为什么不是医生呢
Why didn't I become a doctor?
为什么我会缩小 为什么我的妻子抛弃了我
Why did I downsize? Why did my wife abandon me?
杜赞 你怎么刚好就是我的邻居
Dusan, how did you just happen to be my neighbor?
还有 玉兰  为什么你是
And-And Ngoc Lan, why are you
在那个盒子里唯一的幸存者
the only person who survived that box
你那天是真的碰巧
and you just happen to be cleaning
在打扫杜赞的房子吗
Dusan's place on that day?
而且你没有失去你的腿
And-And had you not lost your leg,
我不是没想过试着帮助你 可是就像以前一样
I wouldn't have tried to help you, which, as usual,
我搞砸了
I screwed up.
为什么我又把事情搞砸了
And why did I screw it up?
这样我就可以
So that I could be here
在正确的时刻进入这个隧道
right at the exact moment to go down into that tunnel.
我终于有机会去做点正事了
I finally have a chance to do something that matters.
保罗 拜托 你在说胡话
Oh, Paul, come on, now you're talking crazy.
那些人是很棒 但是
These people, they're wonderful, but--
像个邪教
It's like a cult.
他们就是邪教 你知道的 可能已经灭绝了
It's a cult. You know, and the extinction, well,
不可能发生在现在 但是几百年前可说不好
it's not gonna happen for, you know, maybe few hundred years.
这些都和你无关 忘了吧
Has nothing to do with you. Forget it.
另外 你认为他们不会假装表现成正常人那样吗
Besides, you think they won't behave like people always behave?
他们都会疯掉然后互相残杀
They're all gonna go insane down there and kill each other.
在我们这么做之前 他们早已经灭绝了
They'll go extinct long before we do.
别担心 亲爱的 他就是自言自语
Don't worry, darling. He said it himself.
他几乎没做成什么事情过
Nothing he ever wants to do works out.
今天天气不错 是吧
It's a beautiful day, huh?
我的意思是 知道这次是我最后一次看到真正的太阳以后
I mean, knowing this is the last time I'll see the real sun,
太阳看起来 很有 活力
it makes it so... vibrant.
我问你问题 你告诉我真话 可以吗
I ask you question. You say me truth. Okay?
当然了
Of course.
那天晚上在船上
Other night on boat...
你因为什么和我发生关系
what kind of fuck you give me?
什么
What?
你给我的是什么炮？
What kind of fuck you give me?
什么 我不懂
What kind? I don't...
美国人 八种不同的炮
American people, eight kind of fuck.
是因为爱 因为恨 还是只是为了做爱而做爱
Love fuck, hate fuck, sex-only fuck,
是分手炮 和好炮
break-up fuck, make-up fuck,
酒后炮 友情炮 还是同情炮
drunk fuck, buddy fuck, pity fuck.
好吧 我不知道你从哪听来这个的
Okay, I-I have no idea where you heard that.
第三个寄宿家庭
Third host family.
好吧 这些都是错的
Okay, Th-that is just wrong.
我和你发生关系  是一种全方位
Okay, there's a whole spectrum
的情感动力驱使的
of-of emotions and- and motivations.
还有不要说 “操” 这是脏话
And don't say "fuck", i-it's vulgar.
说别的来代替 比如做爱之类的
Say something else like, you know, "make love" or I don't know.
所以 是因为爱我吗
So... was love fuck?
好吧 你提这些到底想干什么
Okay, what is this all about?
你找到我 你想帮助我
You look for me, you want help me,
你和我做爱
you make fuck with me,
现在你在装傻充愣吗
now you go down stupid hole.
所以我试着去思考
So I try to think
你到底是因为什么而和我做爱
what kind fuck you give me.
现在我觉得可能是同情炮了
I think maybe pity fuck.
因为我的腿
For leg.
不是的 玉兰
No, no, Ngoc Lan,
我真的非常关心你
I care about you deeply.
你是如此的与众不同
You are such an extraordinary person
我只是很佩服你
and I just admire you so much.
更重要的是
More than anything,
我希望你和我一起走
I want you to come with me.
人们都说我很坚强
People always say me I strong.
好的 可能因为我来自越南
Okay, maybe Vietnam
我组织了很多次抗议
I organize many protest,
在两年的监禁中生存下来
survive two year prison
被惩罚缩小
punish me make small.
我是唯一一个在电视盒子里存活下来的人
I only person survive TV box.
我没有脚来走路
I walk around no foot.
我照顾别人
Take care of other people.
但是我是个女人
But I woman.
我也有感情
Feeling.
真的抱歉
I'm sorry.
我真的很抱歉
I really am.
我很容易就知道你的本质
It's so easy for me to see who you are.
但是 如果我不这样做 那我是谁呢
But if I don't do this, who am I?
我的意思是 真的 我存在的意义是什么呢
I mean, really. Who am I?
你是保罗·萨弗拉尼克
You Paul Safranek.
你是个好人
You good man.
看 那边有蝴蝶
Look, there's butterflies!
看 玉兰 是蝴蝶
Look, Ngoc Lan! Butterflies!
蝴蝶 蝴蝶
Kon booyem! Kon booyem!
我想 就到这里吧
I guess this is it.
康拉德
Konrad.
遇到你真的很高兴
Very nice to have met you.
我也是
Pleasure was mine.
祝你好运 保罗
Good luck in there, Paul.
保重自己
Take care of yourself.
我会的
I will.
你也是
You too.
我会想念我的搞笑邻居的
I will miss my funny neighbor.
你的圣经
Your bible.
可是这个是越南语的
But it's in Vietnamese.
文字不重要
Words not matter.
记住我
Remember me.
你现在走吧
You go away now.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
你好
Hi, uh...
只是我认为 还是咱们都在上坡
Is it just me or are we walking uphill?
是的 为了防止洪水
Yes. Prevents flooding.
- 唐德 - 噢 嗨 我是保罗
-Tunde. -Oh, hi. Paul.
就爬几个小时就到了
It's just a few hours climb
在我们下到地下室之前
before we begin the descent to the vault.
整个过程大概多久
Well, how long is the whole walk?
十一个小时 差不多吧
Eleven hours. Something like that.
我们下面见 不要脱水了
See you down there. Stay hydrated.
等一下
Wait!
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
-等等 我的行李 - 别拿了
-Wait, my bag. -Leave it.
不不不
No, no, no!
我就说过这个家伙什么都干不成
I told you nothing ever works out for this guy.
- 把我的东西扔出来 - 这里要爆炸了 快跑吧
-Get my bag out! -It's going to blow! Run!
保罗
Paul!
玉兰
Ngoc Lan!
我想着你之前说过的那些话
I was thinking about what you were saying.
然后我意识到你是对的
And I realized you were right.
我是保罗萨弗兰内克
I am Paul Safranek.
还有你问的那个
And what you were asking...
我是因为爱你才和你做爱的
It was a love fuck.
我想了
And to think...
一整天这些事情
one day all of this...
现在你可能知道
Now maybe you understand little bit
电视盒子中幸存后是什么感觉了
how I feel after survive TV box.
当你知道死亡即将来临
When you know death come soon,
你会更仔细的观察身边的事情
you look around things more close.
在这里等着 我很快回来
Wait here, I'll be right back.
我也想去 我想看罗萨的小孩
I want go too. I want see Rosa new baby.
不 明天再去看小孩 外面是倾盆大雨
No, see the baby tomorrow, it's pouring.
快点回来
Hurry.
别忘了我们还得去看那个菲律宾男人
Don't forget we still need go see Filipine man,
照顾他的手臂
take care for his arm!
我知道了 不要啰嗦了 可以吗
I know. Stop obsessing, will you?
你好 卡德纳斯先生
Hola, Se?or Cardenas.
- 噢 你好 - 你饿了吗
-Oh, Hola, Paul. -Are you hungry?
很饿 你今天给我带什么啦
A lot. What did you bring me today?
嗯 我觉得是鸡肉
Ah, I think it's chicken.
对 鸡肉
Yes, chicken.
谢谢你 保罗
Thank you, Paul.
没关系
Okay, you're welcome.
明天见
See you tomorrow.